<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The maner to dye well An introduction most compendiouslie shewinge the fruytfull remembrance of the last fowre things: that is to say, death, hel, iudgement, and the ioyes of heauen. Gathered out of manye good authors, both comfortable and profitable to the dilligent reader. Learnedly instructing howe to prouide for death.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1578</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 131 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 69 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00614</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1075</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120489</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855685</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855685</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21187</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00614)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21187)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1019:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The maner to dye well An introduction most compendiouslie shewinge the fruytfull remembrance of the last fowre things: that is to say, death, hel, iudgement, and the ioyes of heauen. Gathered out of manye good authors, both comfortable and profitable to the dilligent reader. Learnedly instructing howe to prouide for death.</title>
                  <author>Soto, Pedro de, d. 1563. aut</author>
                  <author>W. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 64, [1] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Richard Ihones,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1578.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: W.B.</note>
                  <note>Includes, with caption title: The maner howe to dye well. Written in Latine by Pedro de Soto.</note>
                  <note>Signatures and pagination continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Death --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21187:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21187:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE MANER TO DYE WELL.</p>
            <p>An Introduction moſt compendiouſlie ſhewinge the fruytfill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of the laſt fowre things: <hi>That is to ſay,</hi> Death, Hel, Iudgement, and The ioyes of Heauen.</p>
            <p>Gathered out of manye good Authors, both comfortable and profitable to the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Reader.</p>
            <p>Learnedly inſtructing howe to prouide for Death.</p>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Richard Ihones. 1578.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:21187:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O ſtirre vp a more diligence of the inwarden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in vs, our Lorde Ieſus putteth foorth this ſimilitud: <hi>knowe you that if the houſhold Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther knew at what time the Theefe would inuade his houſe, he would ſurely watche, and woulde not ſuffer his houſe to bee bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken.</hi> By this Houſehold is vnderſtanded the thoughtes of man, and alſo the invvarde and outward motions and deedes. VVhich houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde vvoulde be to laſciuious and vvanton, if by the diligence of the Father they vvere not corrected and repreſsed. For if the father be vvearie of his care, vvho coulde be able to shevve hovve proude and inſolent the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghtes, eyes, tongue, eares, and other mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers vvoulde become. This houſe is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, vvherein this Father dvvelleth, and gathereth together the treaſure of vertues, for vvhich he doth vvatche diligentlie, leaſt the houſe should be broken vp<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And it is not one, but many Theeues that vvould com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit this buglary and robbery. For euery ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e hath a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ice incident vnto it. The cheefe
<pb facs="tcp:21187:2"/>Theefe is taken to bee the Deuell, againſte whom and all his atmie the ſaide father (if he be not negligent) doth watche and warde his houſe: appointing <hi>Prudence</hi> in the firſte warde, who vnderſtandeth what is to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and what is to be kept out. Next vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her is placed <hi>Fortitude,</hi> to withſtand ſuche enemies as by her warning he ſeeth to come neere. And <hi>Iuſtice</hi> ſitteth in the middeſt, to geue to euerie one his owne. And euerie houre is to bee feared, for it is not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en in what houre the theefe wil come. VVe oughte alvvaies to watche, leaſt the ſleepe of ſinne do vnwares creepe vpon vs. Now theſe thinges beeing thus ordered, the <hi>Memorie</hi> of <hi>death</hi> deſireth to come, in and is ſuffered to enter, who being demaunded to ſay what he was, and from whence he commeth. Hee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered that he would ſay nothing except all were commaunded to ſilence. VVho obtey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his requeſt, began in this order: <hi>My</hi> name (ſaith he) is <hi>Memorie of death,</hi> and I foretel you that death is comming. <hi>Prudence</hi> ſpeaking for al, putteth the queſtion, ſaying, VVher is death? <hi>Memory</hi> anſvvereth, I know where he is, for he draweth very nere, but the houre of his comming <hi>I</hi> knowe not. <hi>Prud.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21187:3"/>VVho commeth with him? <hi>Mem.</hi> A num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Deuilles bringing with them greate bookes, in which are written the offences of man, and they claime thoſe whoſe ſinnes are written therein, and they will violentlie draw with them both their ſoules and bodies to hel. <hi>Prudence.</hi> VVhat thing is hell? <hi>Mem.</hi> Hel is a place of vnmeſurable ſorowes, miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and darknes, there is eternal horror, there is no hope of goodnes nor ſeperation from euyl. Euery man that is there hateth himſelfe and al others. There is weping and gnashing of teeth. There is no voyce there heard but Alas, Alas, Alas, they haue no vvord but A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las. The deuelishe tormentors doo tormente and are tormented, and of them there shall neuer be ende nor remedie. Suche a place is Hel, and a thouſande times worſe. <hi>Prudence.</hi> O God what shall wee doo? My brethren, heare mine aduiſe, and geue me yours. Be ye faithful, watche and pray, doo good, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the ſighte of men, but in the ſighte of God. <hi>Temperaunce.</hi> Let vs goo before his face with harty repentaunce, and let vs prayſe him in Pſalmes. Bee you ſober and watche. <hi>Fortitud.</hi> Vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom do you ſtay? Be ſtrong in fayth, Comfort your ſelues in our Lorde,
<pb facs="tcp:21187:3"/>Arme your ſelues with the armour of God, Take vppon you the harneys of Iuſtice, the target of Faith, and the ſworde of the holie Ghoſt, which is the word of God. <hi>Iuſtice.</hi> Let vs lyue ſober, iuſt, and godlie. Sober to our ſelues, iuſt to our neighbours, and godlie to God. Let vs not do that to others, vvhich vve vvould not haue done vnto our ſelues. <hi>Prud.</hi> Behold another Meſſenger verie comelie and pleaſaunt, vvho ſeemeth to bring ſome good newes. <hi>Iuſtice.</hi> Let him come in, peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he wyl make vs mery: for this firſt meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger hath terrified vs. <hi>Prudence.</hi> I vvill ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit him. Come in. VVho art thour <hi>Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</hi> I am called, <hi>The loue of eternal lyfe.</hi> Keepe ſilence, for I can not be heard vvhere tumult is. <hi>Iuſtice.</hi> Yf vve did keepe ſilence vvhilſt the <hi>Memory of death</hi> ſpake, of iuſtice we ought to be ſilent when thou ſpeakeſt. <hi>Deſire of eternal lyfe.</hi> I haue ſeene ſuch thinges as no man is vvorthy to ſpeake of. I ſawe God, the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of the vndeuided Trinitie, but yet as it vvere through a glaſſe: that brightnes vvas ſo cleare, that mine eyes daſled to beholde that clearenes vvhich paſſeth all vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Yet notwithſtanding I behelde a litle vvhyle our Lorde Ieſus ſitting on the right
<pb facs="tcp:21187:4"/>hande of his father, who did ſo farre excel all creaturs, that the Angels themſelues deſire to beholde and looke vpon him. And I ſawe vppon his bodye the woundes of his paſsion, wherewith he redeemed vs. But not being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble any long time to looke vpon this bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the ſonne of God, I turned mine eyes vpon the orders of Angels, that ſtand before God. I behelde alſo the Prophets, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and Martirs, and an innumerable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie of bleſſed Soules, from whoſe eyes God hath waſshed awaie all teares: they doo ſee the king in his Maieſtie, and were all appareled in long white garmentes, lyuing a lyfe without ende.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poems">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:21187:4"/>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>Of the fall of man, and the puniſhment by death for the ſame, and of the vncertaine howre of death.</head>
               <l>BY ſhine againſt the lyning Lorde,</l>
               <l>olde <hi>Adam</hi> our firſt Sire,</l>
               <l>Death to him ſelfe and al his ſéede</l>
               <l>hath gayned for his hyre.</l>
               <l>Mortalitie and temporal death</l>
               <l>this gift our Parents wonne,</l>
               <l>In Paradiſe the fruite forbyd,</l>
               <l>to eate when they begonne.</l>
               <l>Firſt ſinne began, and after death</l>
               <l>in haſte dydit enſue:</l>
               <l>By whome ech man muſt paſſe herehence,</l>
               <l>as ſure as God is true.</l>
               <l>Leſt ſome men would them ſelues extol,</l>
               <l>too farre aboue the reſt,</l>
               <l>If that they ſhoulde in freedome quite,</l>
               <l>eſcape this feareful blaſt.</l>
               <l>Then Death nothing more certen is,</l>
               <l>no doubt thereof we ſee,</l>
               <l>But no man knoweth the houre ne place,</l>
               <l>nor what his ende ſhal bee.</l>
               <l>Whether by dint of edged ſword,</l>
               <l>or heate of flaming fyre,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21187:5"/>
               <l>Or roaring wanes of raging ſeas,</l>
               <l>pale Death ſhall paye his byre.</l>
               <l>No place nor time there is, but Death</l>
               <l>in watche and wayte doth lye,</l>
               <l>Man to intrappe, if that he can</l>
               <l>vnarmed him eſpie.</l>
               <l>No ſhadowe darke on maſſie corps,</l>
               <l>more duely doth attende,</l>
               <l>Then lurking death, who alway ſéekes,</l>
               <l>Man to confounde and ende.</l>
               <l>What man is he that ſtandeth ſure,</l>
               <l>tyll night to drawe his breath?</l>
               <l>Our life beeing the open way</l>
               <l>that ſtraight doth leade to death.</l>
               <l>The wiſe therefore remembring oft,</l>
               <l>that once he needes muſt dye,</l>
               <l>His lyfe at euerie howre to yeelde</l>
               <l>prepareth wyllingly.</l>
               <l>Death at the gates of olde men is,</l>
               <l>and preſt to youth alſo:</l>
               <l>But neither knoweth the certen howre,</l>
               <l>when they away muſt go.</l>
               <l>Let vs therfore, not knowing when</l>
               <l>God ſhall vpon vs call,</l>
               <l>Prepare our ſelues in readineſſe,</l>
               <l>both ſoule, minde, harte and all:</l>
               <l>Yeelding our ſelues vnto the Lorde,</l>
               <l>whylſt we our health enioy,</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:21187:5"/>
               <l>Not waſting time by poſting off,</l>
               <l>leaſt we our ſelues annoy.</l>
               <l>Euen like as death doth finde the man,</l>
               <l>ſo man the death ſhal finde,</l>
               <l>For perfect men in ſafetie</l>
               <l>do dye with ioyfull minde.</l>
               <l>With hope of blyſſe the iuſt doth ende</l>
               <l>their lyfe in quiet reſt,</l>
               <l>And wicked men full deſperate,</l>
               <l>doo ende in cares oppreſt.</l>
               <l>Therefore to auoide theſe dangers all,</l>
               <l>keepe thou theſe verſes in minde,</l>
               <l>Which I amongſt the learned workes,</l>
               <l>of godlie men doo finde.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>¶ Of Death, Iudgement, Hell, and Heauen.</head>
               <l>EChe thing returnes to maſſie earth,</l>
               <l>and endes where it begunne:</l>
               <l>Freſh flowres and all that beareth breath,</l>
               <l>as ſhades away doth runne.</l>
               <l>Nothing for long accompted is,</l>
               <l>that muſt in time decay:</l>
               <l>To morrowe next perhaps ſhal be</l>
               <l>my death and dying day.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21187:6"/>
               <l>This preſent day may likewiſe be,</l>
               <l>the laſt day of my dayes,</l>
               <l>Wherein appoynted is that I.</l>
               <l>muſt dye without delayes.</l>
               <l>No hope of dooing wel is left,</l>
               <l>after that deadful day:</l>
               <l>That day in ioy without al greefe,</l>
               <l>To paſſe God ſende I may,</l>
               <l>It is great folly to accompt,</l>
               <l>long time here to endure,</l>
               <l>Séeing that none one day to liue,</l>
               <l>himſelfe can wel aſſure.</l>
               <l>Oft to accompt or mencion make,</l>
               <l>of dayes, it is but vayne,</l>
               <l>Since reſtful day, or quiet houre,</l>
               <l>none hath, without great paine.</l>
               <l>Haue thou as long a time and race,</l>
               <l>as thou doth luſt to runne,</l>
               <l>As ought of nought was made in fine,</l>
               <l>ſo ought to nought muſt turne.</l>
               <l>A thouſand thouſand men haue bene,</l>
               <l>and thouſand of thouſands eke.</l>
               <l>VVhoſe bones in earth conſumed are,</l>
               <l>whoſe fame is nowe to ſeeke,</l>
               <l>A iuſt rewarde for their deſertes,</l>
               <l>doth onely nowe remayne,</l>
               <l>And for their déedes by iudgment iuſt,</l>
               <l>they ſuffer ioy or payne.</l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:21187:6"/>
               <l>Beholde that feareful iudgement iuſt,</l>
               <l>for one ſhal geue the dome,</l>
               <l>VVho doth appoynte that trembling day,</l>
               <l>when he thereto wyl come.</l>
               <l>Dread, feare, and caſt thy count therfore,</l>
               <l>prepare thy harte, I ſay:</l>
               <l>Liue thou as though death preſent were,</l>
               <l>thy due preparde to pay.</l>
            </div>
            <div type="poem">
               <head>¶ Of the houre of death worthye of often repetition.</head>
               <l>REmember oft, O mortal man,</l>
               <l>conſider in thy minde,</l>
               <l>VVhat ſoden feare and terror great,</l>
               <l>thy ſoule is like to fynde:</l>
               <l>VVhat pinching wormes begin to fret,</l>
               <l>the hart on euery ſide,</l>
               <l>VVhen ſoule from fleſh, &amp; life from man,</l>
               <l>begins away to ſlide.</l>
               <l>Ten thouſand griefs begins to paine,</l>
               <l>the wicked ſoule with woe,</l>
               <l>VVhen from the priſon of the fleſhe,</l>
               <l>away it needes muſt goe,</l>
               <l>It doth bewayle with ſtreames of teares,</l>
               <l>the vayne beſtowed time,</l>
               <l>VVherein it might ful leaſurely,</l>
               <l>repent eche ſinful crime:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21187:7"/>
               <l>And bitterlie with ſcryching cryes,</l>
               <l>it makes a rufull mone:</l>
               <l>To ſee the time of ſtrict reuenge,</l>
               <l>that drawes ſo hardlie on.</l>
               <l>It ſeekes a whyle then to remaine,</l>
               <l>in hope ſome mendes to make:</l>
               <l>No ſute maye then preuayle, but that</l>
               <l>the fleſhe it muſt forſake.</l>
               <l>Full fayne it would recouer againe</l>
               <l>the ioye which it hath loſt,</l>
               <l>All is in vaine, it wyll not be,</l>
               <l>away the ſoule muſt poſt.</l>
               <l>But looking backe it ſéeth againe,</l>
               <l>when it was wald with bones,</l>
               <l>The whole full courſe of paſſed lyfe</l>
               <l>all preſentlie at once.</l>
               <l>And taking yet more earneſt viewe,</l>
               <l>it ſéeth, not farre beſide,</l>
               <l>The infinite Eternitie,</l>
               <l>that neuer away wyl ſlide:</l>
               <l>Then trikling teares by watred leares,</l>
               <l>in floudes for gréefe doth runne,</l>
               <l>For loſing al the heauenly ioyes,</l>
               <l>that eaſly mought bene wonne:</l>
               <l>Intiſementes fowle of filthy fleſhe</l>
               <l>iuſt cauſe of greefe then brings,</l>
               <l>For that by them the ſwéete delight</l>
               <l>of heauen and heauenlie thinges:</l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:21187:7"/>
               <l>From ſinfull ſoule for euer, alas,</l>
               <l>remediles is reft,</l>
               <l>And endles paines by iuſt deſart,</l>
               <l>by God to it is left.</l>
               <l>It bluſheth for that the ſinfull fleſh</l>
               <l>it dyd ſo much ſet by,</l>
               <l>The foode of gréedie ſcrauling wormes</l>
               <l>in graue when it doth lye:</l>
               <l>Forgetting quite it ſelfe, alas,</l>
               <l>which if it had done wel,</l>
               <l>To Angels might compared be,</l>
               <l>that in the heauens doo dwel.</l>
               <l>O howe the ſoule confounded is,</l>
               <l>when it doth ſée with eyes,</l>
               <l>The perfect glée that was and is</l>
               <l>aboue the ſtarrie Skies:</l>
               <l>With fléeting ſtoudes of cares, I ſaye,</l>
               <l>the doleful ſoule is toſt,</l>
               <l>When it doth ſee the heauenly health,</l>
               <l>that it hath vainely loſt.</l>
               <l>For vading glorie of the worlde</l>
               <l>in this poore mortall lyfe,</l>
               <l>Wherein we ſee nothing is had</l>
               <l>without debate and ſtrife.</l>
               <l>When the blacke vale of miſerie</l>
               <l>it doth from farre beholde,</l>
               <l>It wondreth at the ſhyning light</l>
               <l>of heauen, more pure then golde:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21187:8"/>
               <l>It doth then ſée the wauering worlde</l>
               <l>that ſéemde to it moſt bright.</l>
               <l>To be none other but a clowde</l>
               <l>more darke then drowpy night.</l>
               <l>How godly, harde, and ſtrict a life,</l>
               <l>the ſoule woulde vndertake,</l>
               <l>What faſtings great, what promiſe large</l>
               <l>what holy vowes would make:</l>
               <l>To get by grace ſome ſpace of tyme,</l>
               <l>wherein it might repent</l>
               <l>The vaine ſurpaſſed courſe of life,</l>
               <l>that earſt in ſinne was ſpent.</l>
               <l>But when the daſled eyes begins</l>
               <l>to looſe their wonted ſight,</l>
               <l>And holo we cheſt yet feble pants,</l>
               <l>and looſing neare his might.</l>
               <l>The ratling throte doth faintly breath</l>
               <l>the téeth waxe blacke and ruſt,</l>
               <l>The lippes becommeth pale and wan,</l>
               <l>the toung is thicke and thurſt,</l>
               <l>And euerie lym neare ſtyffe and colde:</l>
               <l>when theſe doo play their parte,</l>
               <l>As verie ſignes and tokens true</l>
               <l>of Death his pearſing darte.</l>
               <l>Then al his wicked works and thoughts,</l>
               <l>as witneſſe forth are brought,</l>
               <l>And ſtrongeſt euidence they geue</l>
               <l>gainſt him that them haue wrought,</l>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:21187:8"/>
               <l>He no where then can fire his eyes,</l>
               <l>but there they preſent are,</l>
               <l>And as his ſtrongeſt enimies,</l>
               <l>they worke his greateſt care.</l>
               <l>Huge routes of vgly dreadfull douyls</l>
               <l>on tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſide ſtandeth n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re,</l>
               <l>The vertues all on thother ſide,</l>
               <l>with Angels paſſing cleare:</l>
               <l>And in the midſt betwixt them both</l>
               <l>by iuſt and vpright dome,</l>
               <l>Its clearely iudged to whether ſide</l>
               <l>the wand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing ſoule ſhall come.</l>
               <l>If in the pathe of vertue true,</l>
               <l>the ſoule did runne her race,</l>
               <l>Then do the Angels euery one</l>
               <l>craue that it maye haue grace.</l>
               <l>With pleaſaunt heauenly harmonie,</l>
               <l>full ſweete they do allure,</l>
               <l>The ſoule with them in heauen to go,</l>
               <l>they earneſtly procure,</l>
               <l>But if the ſoule all blurred be,</l>
               <l>with blottes of filthy ſinne,</l>
               <l>Then war like troupes of hateful deuils,</l>
               <l>agaynſt the ſoule doo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iune:</l>
               <l>And ſodenly in boy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rous wiſe,</l>
               <l>alheadlong downe doth caſt,</l>
               <l>The guyltie ſoule eternally,</l>
               <l>to he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they pul at laſt.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:21187:9"/>
               <l>In ambuſhe they in priuie wiſe</l>
               <l>the waye doo al beſet,</l>
               <l>Thereby the ſoule to ſtop and ſtay,</l>
               <l>and it from heauen to let.</l>
               <l>By calling theſe and ſuch like thinges,</l>
               <l>to minde with inwarde thought,</l>
               <l>Al raging fleſhlie luſt we ſhal</l>
               <l>deſpiſe and ſet at nought:</l>
               <l>And weigh as thinges of litle weight</l>
               <l>al worldlie pleaſures vaine.</l>
               <l>Forſaking quite thentiſements ſweete,</l>
               <l>of hoores and hooriſhe traine.</l>
               <l>Applying our ſtudies by ſtedfaſt faith</l>
               <l>to God in godlineſſe,</l>
               <l>VVe ſhal (I truſt) by Chriſt at laſt</l>
               <l>be plaſt with Saintes in bliffe.</l>
               <l>Praiſe be to God our Sauiour,</l>
               <l>and to his name alſo,</l>
               <l>VVho graunt that to his glory we,</l>
               <l>all thinges by him may do.</l>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:21187:9"/>
            <head>¶ A redie Inſtruction, and godly exerciſe for an happy death, ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken as it were in the perſon of Chriſt vnto the Soule. Tranſlated out of the Booke called, <hi>Pharetra diuini amoris.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Thou ſoule, as nothing maketh the loue of the worlde to ſeeme more foliſhe, and ſooner pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoketh vnto thee, the happy contempt of al things which are created, then the true conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this ſhort lyfe, &amp; due regarde of temporal death, by which death al worldly endeuours, all earthly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, all vading pleaſures, all vaine thoughts, al hurtful deſires, &amp; tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitorie ioye doth periſh: So nothing doth more reioyce the louing ſoule, then that it beleueth &amp; hopeth to be aſſociated vnto me, &amp; to be altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther drowned in me. Where hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward there ſhalbe no euyl, no ſin,
<pb facs="tcp:21187:10"/>no ſeperation, no daunger, no feare, nor griefe, where in perfect charitie the ſoule ſhal continuallie praiſe, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies magnifie, ſtedfaſtly obey, and perfectlie pleaſe me. And lykewiſe it ſhal continuallie be with me, where it ſhall neither requyre, loue, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect any thing beſides me, but I ſhall be the ſole poſſeſſor of it. And for ſo much as theſe things ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not perfeet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie happen vnto thee in this lyfe, tyll ſuch time as thou ſhalt be plaſt with me in my kingdome, where al thy deſyre ſhal be ſatiſfied in louing and praiſing me, where I ſhal be al in al: Therefore thou doſt iuſtly require, &amp; with al thy hart mayſt lawfully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is contained in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> praier which I haue left with thee, which peticion is, <hi>Let thy kingdome come.</hi> Therefore (my Daughter) if thou doſt entirely loue me, if ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>glie thou affecteſt to come to heauen, if ferue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie thou requyreſt to ſee thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which is this eſtate whereof
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:21187:10"/>I do ſpeake: then in this maner with ſignes praye thou, that my kingdom maye come. Wherein thou ſhalt be vnited vnto me in perfect charitie, and altogether drowned in me. And for that (as I haue ſayde) this can not be, but after death, which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed my Sainctes in patience of lyfe, to wyſhe for death, which is the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie porte or entrie vnto life. Wherby thou mayſt ſee that the ſoule which perfectlie loueth mee, feareth not death. For what doth the ſoule looſe by departing out of this vnhappye life? ſurely nothing but the waye to offende, ſnares of ſinne, occaſions of ruine, deceiptes of enimies, hir owne proper fragilitie and feare<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſuch like innumerable daungers, which do blinde, weake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and chafe the ſoule (paſſing ouer the labors of the body) which are alwayes changeable and vnſtable.</p>
            <p>The ſoule in this worlde wiſheth for many thinges that ſhould not be
<pb facs="tcp:21187:11"/>obtained, not knowing that which it would haue. It coueteth &amp; deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth many things which can not be. The ſoule being ignoraunt &amp; blinde in many things, walketh in dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger and darkneſſe, not knowing howe it may be ridde from them. Why then ſhould not the ſoule willingly wiſh, and hartelie reioyce, to ſee it ſelfe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from theſe innumerable ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes and heapes of daungers?</p>
            <p>O thou ſoule, what doeſt thou feare? Why wyſheſt not thou for death? Seeing thou art not hurt by death, nor yet canſt looſe any thing by death, if thou haue forſaken y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue of al worldly things. Wherfore I tel thee, it is daungerous to loue any earthly thing. For to tel thee truely, I ſay that by louing them, thou im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braceſt very daunger it ſelfe. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I as one that tedreth thy welth, do admoniſh thee, that thou before thy death wilt quite forget al earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly loue, and feare not death if I be he
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21187:11"/>whome thou doeſt onely loue in this life. Reioyce then that thou doeſt die, for that is the onely meane wherby thou mayſt come to me. But perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture thou feareſt ſomewhat els, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loſſe of worldly goodes, or ſome other like thing: Knowe thou then, that there is nothing in this world, whatſoeuer it bee that thou doeſt poſſeſſe (be it neuer ſo greeuous vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee) but needes thou muſt forgoe the ſame. Thou art likewiſe in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme feare, and ſtandeſt in great doubt, whether thou arte worthy to be beloued or hated of me. Thou knoweſt not how I wyl accept thee, neither whether I ſhal receyue thee to peace or paine. O my daughter, the knowl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dge of theſe things belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth not vnto thee. Wherfore ſtay &amp; holde thy ſelfe contented for a while. For although thou doeſt all thy lyfe tyme and at the verie howre of thy death continue in my faith, &amp; fear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt, &amp; hopeſt in me: yet canſt thou not for
<pb facs="tcp:21187:12"/>al this of thee ſelfe either liue a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect life, or dye a godly death. For only by me thou doſt attayne &amp; come to eyther of theſe. Howe thinkeſt thou then, if I geue thee grace to liue well, am I not likewiſe able to graunt that thou ſhalt dye a happie death? Seeing then that thou haſte and getteſt al thinges by mee, why doeſt thou aſſure thee ſelfe of thone doubting and diſpairing in thother? for thou canſte not of thee ſelfe, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther liue nor dye wel. Truſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in me, caſt al thy care vpon me, turne al thy greefe vpon mee, for as in thy life time, ſo neither at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> howre of thy death canſt thou of thee ſelfe withſtande anye temptation, nor eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape any offence. If in thy lyfe tyme I did not forſake thee. If in time of temptation I did ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly aſſiſt thee, and ſtrengthned and enabled thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thine aduerſaries: I wil like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe doe the ſame for thee at the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry laſt houre.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:21187:12"/>
            <p>Thou doeſt neuer go armed with thine owne armour into the feelde, but alwayes preſumeſt vppon mee. If thou wilte leane and ſtaye thee ſelfe vpon me, I wyll fight for thee, and I beeing thy champyon and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendour, what ſhouldeſt thou then neede to feare, whiche (in reſpecte of thy ſelfe) art of no value? And for the manner and order of thy death take thou no care, for no kinde of tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral death can hinder the Iuſte. Care thou not therefore after what ſorte thou dyeſt, whether in thy bedde, or in the feelde, for that ought not to be feared. After what ſorte ſoeuer thy life is bereft iro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee, eyther by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence or otherwiſe, care thou not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is natural to dye. If there bee one kind of temporal death happier then another, then were my Saints vnhappie, of whome, the greateſt number (in the ſighte of the worlde, and to the iudgement of men) ended their liues with moſte vyleſt death.
<pb facs="tcp:21187:13"/>Which of my holye Martyres hath paſt ouer his full courſe, &amp; ended his lyfe by natural death? Which of the Martyrs is there y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hath bene done to death, eyther vpon the painefull croſſe or by force of wylde beaſtes, or by rage of flaming fyre, or by dint of cruell Tirauntes ſworde? Not one truely. It hindreth not therefore any whit, whether thou dieſt, eyther by the raging peſtylence, or by the ſenceleſſe diſeaſe of Apoplexa, or any other death, eyther in thy bedde at home or in the feelde abroade. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware and watche thou onely, that thou maiſt be found in perfect fayth, hope, and charitie, and then no kinde of death nor funeral can hinder thee.</p>
            <p>Although I ſpeake to thee (O be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued ſoule) I do meane and ſpeake theſe thinges alſo to thoſe which are as yet vnperfect, aduiſing and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayling you al to loue innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie, and hate euyl. What ſoule ſoeuer thou be that offendeſt, be ſory and repent,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21187:13"/>and ſo repent (if thou doeſt meane to reape the fruites of true repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance) that thou doo not returne to thine olde ſinnes, nor to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> occaſions ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Looke alwayes for death, and ſo prepare thee ſelfe for it, as though euerie howre ſhould be the inſtaunt therof. And leſt weake ſoules ſhould lacke any kinde of godlie inſtruction, whereby they might the better pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide them ſelues to dye; I wyl adde more to this which I haue ſayde: Marke well the wordes of mine A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle (which thing the matter it ſelf doeth plainely ſhewe.) You haue no ſtedfaſt dwelling, nor permanent cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, ſayth he, in this tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſitory world: for ſuch a cittie is onely to be looked for in the worlde to come, vnto the which this world is nought but the way and pilgrimage, which iourney and pilgrimage is ended when your life is determined. Death is the end of al men, that boundeth and leadeth directly from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pilgrimage wherein
<pb facs="tcp:21187:14"/>you now are, vnto the region wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto you caſt your courſe, in ſuche dyrect ſorte, that there is none other way or gate, through which you ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enter or departe out of this Pylgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage into your countrey, but onelie by death.</p>
            <p>As there is no aſſuraunce of lyfe, ſo there is an aſſured certenty of death: but this indyfferent betweene the good and the euyll, that being mixt in this perigrination, they be al but ſtraungers, and they al do long to come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſed kingdom, although they al walke not in the ryght path. Al you ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as you are in this iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, although you ſtray, you may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the ryght way againe. And when you come to the ende of your iourney, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the very gates ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, &amp; at the extreme inſtant of death, ſome go from eryle to lyfe, and other ſome go to myſerable and eternall death.</p>
            <p>You ought not therfore lightly to
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:21187:14"/>eſteeme, nor forceleſſe with a negly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent conſcience to conſider in what ſort you ſhoulde come to death. For then muſt you forgoe &amp; leaue behind you al thinges, whatſoeuer you put any truſt or confidence in, whether it be riches, honour, friendes, or any other vanitie whatſoeuer, for at the howre of death they ſhal profite no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but muſt be al left behind, and you fellowleſſe without companye ſhal goe alone before the tribunall ſeate of almightie God, thereto re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue accordinge to your workes.</p>
            <p>What greater blindneſſe &amp; madneſſe maye there be, then to take pleaſure or reioyce in any thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto you whylſt you trauaile in this iourney, or to loue any tranſitorie thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> neither auaileth or profiteth the ſoule. And as it were caſt into a certayne ſodaine madneſſe, with a drye wythered conſcience (without God) to ſeeke for ſuch things as are altogether fleſhly, and raſhly to ruſh
<pb facs="tcp:21187:15"/>and thruſt foorthe after externall thinges onely, neglecting ſlouthful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tyme and godly occaſions, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they might amend their liues, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king no regarde nor heede to the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual eſtate, of their inwarde man. And in this maner you doe runne headlong vnto death. O how many are in this very point deceyued. Loe here how they are intraped, wrapt vp, and taken in the deceytful nettes and priuie ſnares of this tranſitorie and miſerable worlde. See howe vnhappilie they are taken captiues, and compelled to drawe: the yoke of the diuell, that thus vnaduiſedlye come to death, with blinde and hard hartes. O howe vnhappie bee their liues, that neglecting death, prepare not for their owne health. They whiche hinder the ſoule, and with pleaſure pamper theyr fleſhe, forgo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing althinges behouefull and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie for theyr ſaluation, are worthy to be cut of an caſt away.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:21187:15"/>
            <p>Euerie man ought ſo to liue at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery howre, as though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame were the laſt howre of his life, wherein he ſhould go to heare the iudgement of God. And right now (if not oftner &amp; alwaies) he ought to cal preſent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his eyes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dreadful houre of his departure from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſhe: for the ſoule ſhalbe iudged for euery word, work and thought. Alwaies and preſently thou oughteſt ſo to rule thy ſelf, that by thy nowe doing thou ſhouldeſt be found in ſuch a readineſſe, as in tyme to come thou wouldeſt wyſhe thou ſhouldeſt be found in, when vndoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted death ſhal appeare. It is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the parte of a fooliſh and madde harte, to deferre the correction of life vnto that time wherein the ende of lyfe appeareth, and when there is no further hope of life: At what time we ought not neede to be amended, but rather being ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, we ought to meete our God. Departing out of this life, thy ſoule forgoeth not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb facs="tcp:21187:16"/>al offences, but alſo leaueth al o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinges behinde it. And yet art thou not ſayde then to forſake ſinne, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou canſt ſinne no more. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whilſt thou haſt power to ſinne, forſake it, ſeeing that true repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce can neuer be to late: notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that ſuch repentance as is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt howre, is much doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted whether it maye be called true repentance, or not. If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feare of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation do ſo much trouble thee at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> howre of thy death, take heede then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou prepare what remedie thou canſt to preuent the ſame. I feare me, thy feare groweth not by chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (for that thou didſt offence me thy Lord God) but that it commeth on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the proper loue thou beareſt to thee ſelfe. Thy onely cauſe of griefe is, for that by thine owne offences thou haſt gained death and eternall damnation: whereas if thou hadſt truely repented, thy chiefeſt cauſe of ſorowe ſhoulde be, in that thou waſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21187:16"/>vnobedient, ſtubborne, vnthankfull, reprocheful, and that thou yeeldedſt not due honour vnto me. This ouer great lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ting of thine owne cauſe, doth iuſtly argue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if there had bene no daunger, or if ſinne ſhould freelie eſcape vnpuniſhed, thou wouldeſt neuer bewayle thy ſinfull eſtate, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> hadſt continued therein a thouſand yeres. The true repenta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, whereby the ſoule is reconciled vnto me, is grounded only vpon charity, &amp; doth continually lament and repent, that it hath ſo often deſpiſed me, the beſt, the greateſt, &amp; faithfulleſt Lord God, Creator &amp; redemer: And that it hath exalted it ſelf ſo hyely, ſo proud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, ſo arrogantlie and vnobedientlie againſt me, it being but duſt and of no value.</p>
            <p>Whoſoeuer he be that meaneth to dye well, let him (as mine Apoſtle teacheth) lyue ſoberlie, iuſtlie, and godly. For after a good and iuſt life, foloweth an happy death. For the
<pb facs="tcp:21187:17"/>death of my Saints are precious in my ſight, by what death ſoeuer they doe depart out of this life, whether it be by water, or by fyre, or in their beddes, And for a preparation ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto (in the meditation whereof a wyſe man ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth the whole courſe of his natural lyfe) take here this ſhort exerciſe, whereby euery Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian may in ſuche ſorte admoniſhe and direct himſelfe in ſuch order, as he needeth not to feare death, ſo as hee be founde according to this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, it ſhal ſuffice.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Wholſome admonitions to dye.</head>
               <p>WHatſoener things at the howre of thy death thou wouldeſt haue to bee done, doe thou the ſame preſently: and whatſoeuer thou arte by duety bound to doe, commit not the charge thereof vnto others. For if thou thy ſelfe waſt negligent and careleſſe of thine owne wealth and buſines, howe thinkeſt thou that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21187:17"/>wyl take any heede or regarde to thy health? Beleeue not vncerten thinges and vaine promiſes, neither commit thyſelfe to doubtful chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Liue &amp; ſo behaue thee ſelfe, that thou mayſt be ſo quieted in thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, as though this were thy dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing daye. Neuer go vnto thy bedde, before thou haſt accoumpted with thy ſelfe the maner &amp; ſtate of thy life. Examine thy ſelfe, calling thy harte with al thy ſences to iudgement, and knowe whether thou be the better or the worſe for this daye. Neuer go thou to bedde with ſuch a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, wherein thou feareſt to dye. If thou doeſt finde thee ſelfe in ſuch ſtate as thou doeſt feare to die, ſearch out the cauſe therof: for peraduenture there be ſome ſinnes, of the which as yet thou haſt not perfectlie repented thy ſelf, or elſe thou forſakeſt to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge &amp; confeſſe them, or peraduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture thou doeſt refuſe to abſtaine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the occaſions thereof: or thou liueſt
<pb facs="tcp:21187:18"/>vnder the daunger or obedience of ſome man: or as a peruerſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou doſt continue in malice, or in the vniuſt withholding of other mennes goodes: or thou art too much addic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp; bent to the couetous deſyre of worldly wealth &amp; carnal ſenſualitie: or rauiſhed with the vnlawful luſt of ſome creature: or being ſo deepelie drowned in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greedy deſire of earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie &amp; viſible thinges, in ſuch ſort as y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> canſt by no meanes be withdrawen from them, coueting for nothing of that which belongeth to the Soule, fooliſhly looking and lyking in al ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal things, lothing and vomiting out al heauenly thinges. The cauſe that mooueth thee to feare death, is, that thy guyltie conſcience foretel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth thy feareful minde the torments whiche are prouided for thy ſinneful ſoule after thy death. Which ſoeuer of theſe reſteth and raygneth in thee, cutte them off, perſecute them, and with all thyne endeuour doo what
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21187:18"/>lyeth in thee to deliuer thy ſelfe from them. Imbrace my croſſe, and folow my footeſteppes, and they ſhal be a great furtheraunce to thee in this thine attempte, and with rigour of minde &amp; holy hatred againſt thy ſelf, proclayme thou open warre againſt al vyces, with a determinate wyll not to ſinne, renewing oftentymes this holy battayle without ceaſſing: And leaſt thou ſhouldſt be ouerthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen for weakneſſe and want of cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, contemplate and earneſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the examples of me and of my Saints commending thy ſelfe to the prayers &amp; exhortations of good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, repoſing thy ſelfe with inwarde and wholſome inſpiration, be occupied in prayer and godlie reading, be neuer ydle, loue ſolitarineſſe and ſylence. Theſe and ſuch like driue away euyl thoughts fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the harte, &amp; baniſh the feare of death. When thou co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meſt to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende of euery day, ſay vnto thy ſelf, Now my life is ſhortned by one day.
<pb facs="tcp:21187:19"/>And when thou ryſeſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> morning, ſaye: O God I am by one night nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to death then I was.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ An Exerciſe to be vſed in the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or at other times when you thinke conuenient.</head>
               <p>ALmightie and eternall God, my Creator and louer, I praiſe, adore and bleſſe thee, for that in mine offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and vngratefulneſſe thou haſt ſo mercifullie and leyſurelie forborne &amp; ſuffred me to liue euen to this houre, wherunto by thy benefits thou haſt brought me, geuing to me thine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy &amp; reprocheful ſeruaunt, both life &amp; neceſſaries therunto belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ging, appointing Angelles to be my kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers. O good God, who knoweth whether tyll euening my life ſhal be prolonged, or what death is appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted forme. O merciful Lorde God &amp; heauenly father, graunt that I may with harty repentaunce truly repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y ſinnes, &amp; inwardly bewaile that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>et I offended thy godly maieſtie.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21187:19"/>Suffer not my ſoule to departe this body, before it be (through thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie perfectlie reconciled and adopted vnto thee by thy grace) bedeckt with thy merites and vertues, inflamed with perfect charitie, and acceptable vnto thee, according vnto thy wyl.</p>
               <p>O mercifull Lorde Ieſus Chriſte, if thoſe thinges whiche I deſyre doo ſtand with thy pleaſure, grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t them I beſeeche thee. although I be not worthy to be heard: yeelde and geue I beſeech thee, of thine infinite mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, that by the merites of thy paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I may be purged from al my ſinnes. And that at the howre of my death I maye be ſtriken with true and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement contrition, and being knitte with thee in perfect charity, I maye immediatly flit vnto thee my ſweete Redeemer ſafelie and freelie from al dampnation. Neuertheleſſe in al theſe my requeſtes, O beſt beloued Ieſu, I do fully and wholy offer and reſigne my ſelfe vnto thee, to be alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
<pb facs="tcp:21187:20"/>diſpoſed &amp; ordered according to thy wyl, and to ſuffer for thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſake: deſyring this one thing at thy hands, that thou wilt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber my fragilitie, vnworthineſſe, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtableneſſe, &amp; miſeries, together with thine owne goodneſſe and moſt cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable mercy, praying thee neuer to forſake or leaue me, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou wylt alwaies poſſeſſe and gouerne me, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy wyl, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ An oblation of Chriſt, and of his merites, vnto his Father.</head>
               <p>OMnipotent and benigne Father, al the paines, dolours, checkes, puniſhmentes, rebukes and labours of thy onelie begotten Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, lambe immaculate, which he vpon his owne body hath ſuffred for my ſake: his trauels, with the afflie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of al his members for me: his bloudſhed, and feete nayled for me: his moſt noble and godly ſoule ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from his delicate body for mee: his infinite vertues and merites, the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21187:20"/>ſtrength alſo of his body &amp; ſoule, and al thinges y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hare lyfe in him yeelded to death for my redemption: inſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding vnited with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Deitie. Chriſt alſo thy bleſſed ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, God &amp; man omnipotent, both weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned looking downe, &amp; glorious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king myracles, and hanging vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Croſſe: I do here offer vnto thee in exaction &amp; ſatiſfaction of my ſynnes &amp; al the worldes, and in mortifying &amp; extinguiſhing of al my paſſions, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil affections, &amp; ſinful vices, in ſteede and ſupply of al my neglige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and in the laude and prayſe of al thy graces &amp; benefites. O heauenly father, haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſion vpon me for his ſake, haue thou mercie vpon me for the loue of thy beloued ſonne Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>THere be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which doe prefixe a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine kinde of exerciſe vnto them ſelues, as death were preſent, prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring themſelues euerye fyue dayes continually, in ſuche ſorte as though
<pb facs="tcp:21187:21"/>they ſhoulde dye preſently.</p>
               <p>The fyrſt daye, they do remember death, the preſidentes and horror thereof, to whom they do wyllingly yeelde.</p>
               <p>The ſeconde daye, they do thinke vpon theyr ſinnes, and them ſo buſie and diligently they do confeſſe, as though preſently after theyr confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhould die, paſſing ouer that daye in ſobbes and teares.</p>
               <p>The thyrde day, with the greateſt deuotion they can, they do prepare themſelues, comming to the holye Euchariſt, and vittayle themſelues therewith, for theyr reliefe in theyr iourney.</p>
               <p>The fowrth daye, they do continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally pray vnto God for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inſpiration of the holy ghoſt, wherby they may lighten &amp; ſoften the hardnes of theyr hartes: and thus they do continew al that day.</p>
               <p>The fift day, with feruent deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they make theyr humble ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:21187:21"/>vnto God, for a ſpyrituall death, wherby they may perfectlie mortify them ſelues, and yet continually liue to God.</p>
               <p>To ech of theſe dayes a man may applie fyt Pſalmes and Prayers.</p>
               <p>And laſtly they do giue harty tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks to almightie God for his innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble benefits beſtowed vpon them at al times during theyr liues.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Spirituall counſayles at the howre of death.</head>
               <p>MY Daughter, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> beeing brought to infyrmitie, prepare thy ſoule to God, taking ſuch order for thy temporal goodes, that there be no ſtrife nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plaint for them after thy death. Nothing profiteth the ſoule more then to leade a iuſt &amp; innocent lyfe, and to do good to euery man in thine owne life tyme, &amp; whatſoeuer thou wouldeſt that others ſhould do for thee, be thou careful and diligent to do y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame thy ſelfe. If after death thou doſt goe to euerlaſting paine,
<pb facs="tcp:21187:22"/>what doeth the fulfylling of thy Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, the pompe of thy Funeral, almes, or ſacrifice auayle thee after thy death? Do theſe things thy ſelfe in thine owne life dayes, that thou maiſt be deliuered not only fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinne, but alſo increaſed in my grace, thou mayſt eſcape damnation: and I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing thee from thine offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, thou maiſt continue and perceuer in good workes vnto the ende. When death approcheth ſee thou do ridde thy ſelf from al cares and worldlie labours, that with feruent deſire thou mayſt affect to come to me without ſpotte, beeing ful of fayth, not truſting any thing to thine owne workes, but let the hope of thy reliefe be onely plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in mine ineffable mercie. In this faith altogeather betaking thy ſelfe, and al other things which thou haſt in this worlde, vnto my prouident wyl, humblie and deuoutlie receyue thou the Sacraments of my body &amp; blood, which haue theyr vertue only
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21187:22"/>by my merites, and were by me ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto the Church as a treaſure. Although that many men haue ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> times abuſed them, as they haue done many other good things: neuer theleſſe, receiue thou them with a feruent zeale and a ſure fayth, vnto thy euerlaſting ioy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ An Exerciſe, wherein the weake man may reſigne himſelfe. to God.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> My ſaythful louer, O mercyfull Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, graunt that with al my harte and minde I maye perfectly vnderſtande that which I ſaye. As the Harte deſireth to come to the fountaynes of freſhe waters, ſo doeth my ſoule deſire to come to thee, O Lorde. I haue choſen ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to bee an abiect and an vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the houſe of my god, then to dwel in the Tabernacles of ſinners. Bleſſed are they which dwell in thy houſe, O Lord, they ſhal prayſe thee for euer. By ſoule dothe thirſe to
<pb facs="tcp:21187:23"/>come to thee (O Lorde) when ſhal I appeare before thy face. O my ſoule why art thou heauy, why troubleſt thou me? Hope in the Lorde, for I wyl truſt in him, the health of my countenaunce, and my God. Turne thy face vpon me thy ſeruaunt, ſaue me in thy mercie, O Lorde, that I be not confounded foreuer. I cal vpon thee, linger not from me my God. Looke backe and aſſiſt me, a poore man left vnto thee, for thou arte the releeuer of Orphantes, thou art the refuge of al my trouble that compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth me. O my triumph, delyuer me from them that aſſault me. O thou Lorde God of my health, come and helpe me, for thou arte my ſtrength, my helper and refuge, do not forſake me, nor deſpiſe me. O God ſalute me with welcome, beholde I come vnto thee my God, whome I haue neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and deſpiſed, for all the earth is ful of thy mercy. I doe therefore flye vnto thee moſte mercyfull God, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21187:23"/>me according to thy word, (by which thou ſaydeſt, I wyll not the death of a ſinner) and I ſhal lyue, do not conſounde me contrarie to mine expectation. My God, I craue not for this temporal life, but I do onely inuocate and call vpon thee with al my harte, which art the eternal life. Alas my beſt beloued. Alas my only Lord and God, that euer I offended thee, that euer I neglected thy inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations and counſayles, that euer I loued any thing beſides thee, my Lorde God, this is it that repenteth me. I beſeech thee therfore to grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto me, that during my life I maye with al my hart truely &amp; faithful lie repent and bewayle theſe mine offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. I woulde I coulde powre forth and vp before thee, al the droppes of my bloud and teares, in true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce. Lorde Ieſu I craue and loke neyther for death nor life, but onelie for thy good wyl. Let al thinges be done according to thy good wyl and
<pb facs="tcp:21187:24"/>pleaſure. Seeing it pleaſeth thee that I muſt dye, O Ieſu receyue my ſoule, grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that I may haue eternal reſt with thee. If it be thy pleaſure, O Ieſu, that my lyfe ſhal be prolon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, I haue determined with al my harte to beſeeche and aſke, that thou wylt moſt graciouſly graunt it me, through the helpe of thy mercie and grace, &amp; ſo to offer my ſelfe vnto thee as an offering to thy glorie &amp; wyll. O beſt beloued Ieſu, for that I haue paſt ouer my lyfe in contempt of thy glorious name, lyuing out of thine obedience, graunt nowe, I beſeeche thee, that henceforward I may wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtrength of my ſoule and body, and al the reſt of my time grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted by thee, vnto thy glorie and wyl.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Mercyful Ieſu, bee preſent with me, and mercifullye helpe mee in theſe my paynes and miſeries, and if greeuouſer paynes ſhall happen to oppreſſe me (which for mine offences
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21187:24"/>I knowe I haue deſerued farre gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſer &amp; greater then theſe) graunt that I maye ſuffer and beare them paciently. Oſweete Ieſu, although I had neuer offended, nor deſerued puniſhment in thy ſighte, yet to thy glory and wyl, in theſe paynes, as in euerye other, I doe offer and reſigne my ſelfe vnto thy Maieſtie, not tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in mine owne vertue, but only in the multitude of thy merits, vpon which I doe preſume, and doe inuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and call vppon thee, that thou mayſt by thy vertue erect &amp; ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the weaknes and vnſtedfaſtnes of my ſoule, and that thou wilt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort it with ſtrength, and ſtrengthen it with patience, that I doe not fall downe, beeing vanquiſhed with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie and temptation, nor weried with weaknes of minde: but beeing altogeather conſumed in the flame of thy ſweete fyre and loue, I maye onely long for thee, and that wyth a thirſtie appetite I maye coole my
<pb facs="tcp:21187:25"/>thirſt in thee, that I may thinke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee, and altogether long for thee, &amp; that I may forſake, diſdaine, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temne the world &amp; al things therin, &amp; that I may geue thee like thanks, both in ioye and ſorowe.</p>
               <p>O Moſt louing Ieſu, I haue choſen thee, I wiſhe and loke for thee, I runne to meete thee, and I doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce all things that are not of thee. Whatſoeuer thou wilt I wyll: and whatſoeuer thou wylt not, the ſame I wyl forſake. Whatſoeuer thou doeſt deteſt, I doe refuſe it: and whatſoeuer ſhal hereafter happen vnto me co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie to this my preſent minde, I beſeeche thee my God, not to impute the ſame vnto me, neither according vnto that, but accordyng to this preſent choyſe of my ſoule iudge me. For al thinges whiche I ought not to doe, I doe here vtterly forſake them. And if at anye time hereafter I ſhall chaunce by any ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21187:25"/>occaſion to agree to any thing that may be a cauſe to withdraw thy n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> dyd from me, I do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vtterly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tlys ſatile.</p>
               <p>O Lorde I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, if it pleaſe thre, or if if maye ſtande <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thy gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t I be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eche thee, in this my preſent lyfe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, wherein I ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nded, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>om al the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ines <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>uedlie I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ght to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. And that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ned farry afte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Lorde Ieſu <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>¶ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> or l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>therto be ſaye, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> vp on at the howre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſeath.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> IN the name of the Father, and of the Some, and of the holie Ghoſt. I H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a wretched ſynner, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>deemed
<pb facs="tcp:21187:26"/>with the precious bloud of our Lord Ieſus Chriſte, through his greate merry and loue, &amp; not by my merites do confeſſe and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>knowledge openly, eyther by this wryting, or by theſe my wordes, before God omnipotent, and before you that are here as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes (if there needeth any) that I a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>d doo dyethe true ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>unt of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte, as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eth a true Chriſtian. I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue and confeſſe generallie all and euerie parte and Article of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian fayth, wherein euery Chriſtian beleeuer is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>de is beleeue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. And chi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie the v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iuerſall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned in the twelue Articles of the Chriſtian faith, either openly expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or by reaſon excluded. According as through the holye Ghoſte by the twelue Apoſtles, and by the true goſpel they were delyuered vnto vs. And to be ſhorte, I beleeue ſo muche as a true Chriſtian ought. And I do with all my harte reioyce to dye in
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21187:26"/>this immoueable and fyrme Fayth, holding this ſcripture in my handes, and offering it vp, as a moſt defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible and inuinſible ſhield againſt all the inuaſions and deceiptes of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell. And if (which God forbyd, it come to paſſe, that by the temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the diuell, or by the violence of my diſeaſe, I ſhall happen to thinke, ſpeake, or do any thing contrarie to this preteſtation: Or that I ſhall fal into any error, miſbelefe, or diſpaire: Yf any of theſe doo chaunce vnto me I do here in the preſence of you al reuobe, &amp; vtterly renounce the ſame, in ſuch ſorte as I woulde do if I had my perfect ſences. For this I cal you al which are here preſent, &amp; thee my good Angell vnto whoſe cuſtodie I am co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted, that you as witneſſes may teſtifie this my proteſtation and confeſſion, before the omnipotent and righteous Iudge.</p>
               <p>As muche as in me lyeth, I doo here clearely forgeue and remit al in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuries
<pb facs="tcp:21187:27"/>iuries whatſoeuer haue beene done vnto me: And the lyke I do aſke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> theyr handes, who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eit her by word or dee de I haue at any time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. And cheeſſie I do requeſt to bee par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker of the bytter Paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent death of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and that my natural and voluntarie death may, through thy grace, ſtande for al my ſinnes.</p>
               <p>I do alſo intitely reque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and deſire you al that be here preſent, to ſay the Lordes prayer with me, and for me. Our Father which arte in Heauen, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Thy kingdom thing. Thy wyl be done in earth as it is in heauen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eue vs this day out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>yl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e breade. And forgeue vs our treſpaſſes, as we forgeue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs. And leade vs not into temptation. But deliuer vs from al euyl. For thine is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, the power, and the glorie, for euer and euer, Amen.</p>
               <p>Would to God I had neuer ſinned
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21187:27"/>nor offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded againſt my God, nor my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> periors <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> againſt my neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, nor my ſelfe:</p>
               <p>Laſtlie I ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>bes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ghty God, for al his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>wed vpon weſt. And I comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>de my body and ſoule into thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that my ſoule may he ſaued through the bitter paſſion of our Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Chriſt, to whom be prayſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; glory for euer and euer, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Howe feareful and bytter corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral death is of it ſelfe, and the mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> cauſes thereof,</head>
               <p>AS man naturallie deſyreth to be in this worlde, to lyue, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce: So is it alſo natural for him to feare death, and the paines &amp; preſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents thereof. Vertuous and perfect men (not withſtanding) are accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to wyſh for death, wr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ch as it is the ende of the myſeties and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences of this preſent lyfe, &amp; the entry like wiſe into the felicitie and ioye to
<pb facs="tcp:21187:28"/>come. They do therfore couet death, whiche loue no vn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all thing in this lyfe, and deſpiſeth and ſettethat nought al the vanities, pleaſutes, ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, homours, &amp; proſperities of this world, with a moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dent affection aſpyring to the moſt bleſſed ſyght of theyr God, whome aboue al other thinges they do with al their hartes entirely loue, and inwardlie burne with the hartie deſyre of heauenlie pleaſures &amp; eternall wealth, ſaying with the prophet Dauid, As y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hart deſireth to come to the fountaines of freſh waters, ſo doth my ſoule deſire thee, O Lord. My ſoule hath thirſted to come vnto God the lyuing foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine. When ſhal I come &amp; appeare before the face of God? And to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame effect ſayth Paule, I vnhappie man, who wyll deliuer me from the body of this death? That is to ſaye, from this mortal &amp; miſerable body. Alſo, I deſyre to be diſſolued, &amp; to be with Chriſt. Neuertheleſſe, though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21187:28"/>of death of it ſelf be a moſt bytter paine, and that the loſſe of lyfe to a humaine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> is natura<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le fearfull and hor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>, inſomuch that our Lord Ieſus Chriſt (death appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ig) by natural <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of death, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he tooke willingly vpon him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to feare, to ware weerie, and to be heauy. Such w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of death is pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>able, for it withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth man from cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> detectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and from the vanities of this worlde. He that wyl wiſely conſider howe paw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful an ende, howe bytter a death, and howe greeuous a ſorow doth dayly approche vnto him (and peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture is preſentlie at hande) hee wyll re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayne him ſelfe from dyſſolute and vaine ſecutitie, from ſportes, games, and laughters: Saying with Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, I haue accompted laughing for errour: And to myrthe I haue ſayde, Why doeſt thou deceyne in vayne? And that they be ſo in deede, the wyſe Salomon doth in another
<pb facs="tcp:21187:29"/>place witneſſe the ſame. Better it is (ſayeth he) to g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e into a ſorrowfull houſe: then into a ho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ueting houſe. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>thoue (that is the ſorowful houſe) man is admoniſhed of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de of all men, &amp; lyuing he thinketh vpon that which ſhall happen, and is to come. As the Scripture ſayth: Bleſſed is he that is alwayes fearefull. And by this the olde Doctours Hier<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome and Auguſtine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wryte that Plato (that excellent and moſte noble Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher) dyd forgoe the delicate and beautifull Cittie of Athens<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>tayne of his Schollers, chooſing rather to dwell in an olde thinous Vyllage, beeing often with Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes and Tempeſtes wel neare ouerturned ſo that by the frace of daungers and death, they myght in themſelues mortifie the vicas of the fleſhe, &amp; withdraw themſelues from concupiſcence and all other vices.</p>
               <p>For ſo muche as the Gentyles haue done this, howe much more (I praye
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21187:29"/>you) ought Chriſtians to withdraw themſelues from delectations, by remembring the daungers of death? And that by this (the preme ditation of death) there might growe in vs ſuch an healthful feare. The diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of him that dyeth is to be conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, &amp; to behold the preſent howre of the ſeparation of the ſoule from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſhe, whereof man hath a naturall feare, for then man altogeather wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth pale, his feete waxeth colde, his weake hands becommeth blacke, his countenaunce chaungeth colour, his eyes becommeth dimme, and ſinketh in, and for intollerable pangues of paynes they are turned vpwarde. See how his hart waxeth faynt, his forehead ſhrinketh, all his members waxeth flyffe, his chinne falleth, his pulſes chaungeth theyr courſe, &amp; his breath gathering it ſelf from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nermoſt bowels doo altogether for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the body. The paines of death do then appeare, &amp; deadly pangues,
<pb facs="tcp:21187:30"/>ſtinging with the mortal ſtinges the very harte, which fyrſt of al begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to lyue, and laſt of al doth dye. And laſt of al there commeth &amp; brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth foorth a dead ſweate, ſhewing that Nature is ouercome. And thus being vanquiſhed by griefe the ſoule is caſt out from hir dwelling place. If we wyl conſyder this diſpoſition of them that dye, and do dilygentlie imagine, that the lyke wyl ſhort: lie happen vnto our ſelues, there is no doubte but we wyll conſider the healthfull feare of death.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:21187:30"/>
               <head>¶ THE MANER howe to dye well.</head>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Written in Latin by Petrus de Soto.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>L men muſt nedes dye, a puniſhment aſſigned vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs for that ſinne of our fyrſt parentes. Mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie (that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>euitable death) is teſt &amp; caſt vpon vs, for that <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eua</hi> did eate of the forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den fruit, wherby they ſinned againſt the Lord. And as ſinne was firſt com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mited, ſo death preſently folowed. By ſyn they loſt life, &amp; gained death. For as by doing well they ſhoulde haue obteyned immortality to themſelues &amp; their poſterity: ſo by doing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie they haue gained death &amp; mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality to them &amp; vs for euer, from the general ſentence whereof none ſhal eſcape, leſt that any one ſhoulde haue cauſe to exalt himſelf aboue another, if he might freely eſcape the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21187:31"/>
                  <head>The certentie of death, and the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certayne howre thereof.</head>
                  <p>NOthing is more certayne then death, but the howre, the place, and maner thereof, none knoweth. For who is he that knoweth when, where, and after what ſorte he muſt dye? whether he ſhal dye a good, or a ſhamefull death? whether hee ſhall ende his lyfe by ſword, fire, or water, or by any other kynde of death? No not one truely. For death (more dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent then our ſhadows) at al times and places continuallye geueth his attendance, laying for vs his trappe, thinking at euerye houre vnwarely to intrap vs therein. Who is then ſo fooliſh, as to aſſure himſelfe to lyue but tyl night, of what age ſoeuer hee be of? For what other thing is our life, but the verye beaten pathe, and ſtraight way to death? Hee therefore that is wiſe, loketh, &amp; prepareth him ſelfe for death, and at al tymes and in al places is continually ready to dye.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21187:31"/>For death is at the gates of old men, and lyeth in a readines to oppreſſe &amp; ouertake yong men: the houre when the Lorde reſerueth and keepeth to himſelfe, to the ende that we beeing vncertayne when to dye, ſhoulde the rather prepare our ſelues to dy. And whylſt we haue our perfect health &amp; memorie, we ought to acknowledge our redeemer, to cal vpon him, beta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king our ſelues altogether vnto his clemencie &amp; great mercye. And in no wiſe to detract the time to the laſte houre and extreme inſtant of death. For death moſt commonlie aſſaulteth and oppreſſeth thoſe whom he ſeethe moſt vnwilling and the worſt proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. And as death findeth the man, ſo man ſhall finde death. The perfect man dyeth in ſecuritie and gladnes, the iuſt manful of hope, fayth, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured confidence, and the vniuſt dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in ſtare and deſperation.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21187:32"/>
                  <head>VVhy Iuſt men doe wiſhe for death.</head>
                  <p>WE do continually walk amongſt innumerable dangers, that is the dangerous ſnares of our aunciente enimie the diuel, the bloody ſwordes of the wicked, the intollerable gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes, paynes, and labours of the body: The habitation or dwelling place of the body wherein we dwel is rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, the worldely ſea wherein wee fayle is ful of ſtormes &amp; dangerous wrackes, no earthly thing wherein wee can delight our ſelues lacketh great perils, and that wherein wee thinke we finde great felicitie, therin alwayes conſiſteth our moſt miſerie and calamities. But yet our benigne Sauiour doth not without heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prouidence appoynte &amp; ſuffer, that this our mortal life ſhoulde be ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleniſhed and fylled with thoſe ſo great calamities, paynes and perils: And alſo doth (according to his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founde wiſedome) prouidentlye or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyne
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21187:32"/>and appoynte them (I meane thoſe temporal paynes which we do abide (to the ende that wee ſhoulde repent vs of our former ſinnes, and amend our preſent lyfe, and diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to care for the lyfe to come, and that we ſhoulde willingly contemne the worlde, and ſet at noughte this tranſitorie life, erecting and lifting vppe our mindes, ſoules, and hartes vnto the almightie God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> earneſtlye affecting the glorious &amp; euerlaſting life, with feruent deſire from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of our hartes. Our forefathers which in times paſt taſted but verye litle of this glorious and heauenlye ſweetnes, did yet abandon al earthly vanities, abhorred the delight of the world, deſpiſed and quite forgot this tranſitorie life, moſt painfully labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with al diligence to obteine the vnſpeakeable pleaſures of heauen, greedely thirſting for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eternal bliſſe, ſaying with the Apoſtle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> O wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched man, who ſhal deliuer me from
<pb facs="tcp:21187:33"/>this mortal body. My deſire is to be diſſolued, &amp; to be with thee, O chriſt. for as the Harte deſireth to come to the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tains of freſh water<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, ſo doth my ſoule, O Lorde, deſire to come to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hee. Although death bringeth vnto vs ſuche and ſo many plea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>res, and that through it the ſoule is carried thither where it ſhal e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>auy liue: y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> we ought not to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>te nor ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt of our life, which is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lbed by God, neyther ought wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> bee the cauſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s or proc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of our owne death. For as we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> not hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> owne appoyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ment: ſo ought we not to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>rs of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ende, before the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ime appoynted vnto v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by god. Hereby I iudge him to be altogether forgetful of himſelfe, and litle to regarde his owne ſtate, that thinketh his time in this world to be but ſhort, ſeeing it is ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>fent to liue a ſhort time and ſmal age, ſo that we ſpende the ſame in dooing well. For what matter is it wheth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> one dye
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21187:33"/>yong or olde, for ſo much as the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of yeeres, nor length of tyme, do make neyther bleſſed nor vnbleſſed, happy nor vnhappy. And that by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to death (the ende of al humain kinde) we ſhal aryue in a ſafe porte &amp; quiet harborowe, free and ſafe from al the dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous ſtormes &amp; trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome broyles of this worlde.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The death of the iuſt man.</head>
                  <p>NOthing ought to be more wiſhed for, then to be in the handes of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wherein the Soules of the iuſt quietly reſt. Theyr death is accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to the Lorde, if a man maye ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that death, which is the greateſt pleaſure y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> can happen to good men, for it is to them the ende of labour &amp; care, the winning of victory, the way of lyfe, the entrie into perfect ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and ioyning of the ſoule to God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thiefeſt goodnes, which is of al other the greateſt rewarde that men can haue. The departing of the iuſt man
<pb facs="tcp:21187:34"/>from this lyfe, is the vyage and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage from trouble to reſt, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paynes to glory, from pouerty to a kingdom, from feare to ſecuritie, from griefe to ioye, &amp; from death to that lyfe, which onelie ought to be called lyfe. And to conclude, death is nought elſe vnto him but an eſcape from priſonment, a returne from baniſhment, a finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of labours, an arriual to the port of reſt, an ending of pylgrimage, a lyghtning of his burden, a delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce from a ruinous houſe, an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of euylles, an eſcape from daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and paying to nature hir due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and entrye into his countrey of euerlaſting ioye and glorie: By meanes where of that daye wherein the Saintes departe hence, and are receyued into Heauen, is commonlie called their natall daye, for that when they departe hence, then doo they begynne to lyfe, and by dying in this worlde, they enter into a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:21187:34"/>
                  <head>The death of the euyll.</head>
                  <p>THe death of a ſinner is moſt wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched of al euyls, for there by he lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the worlde, the greateſt aſpect &amp; familyer felowſhip of his beſt belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: alſo by it y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule is ſeuered from the body, &amp; is condempned to abide y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> affliction of Hell fyre. For the paines of one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demened ſoule is farre worſe &amp; greeuouſer then al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tormentes of al the holy Martirs, yea though they were al gathered in one. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſinner hath horror &amp; feare at his departing, griefe &amp; ſorow in his iourney, ſhame and confuſion in the ſight of God the vpright iudge, &amp; incredible terror, &amp; dreade in departing from this lyfe, &amp; entring into an vnknowen Region, wherein feareful ſpyrites &amp; wycked Angels meete the ſoule, and pul it to eternal paines.</p>
                  <p>The goodes of the wycked are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided into three: Fyrſt, his ſoule to the diuel: his body to the wormes: &amp; his temporal goodes to his heyres,
<pb facs="tcp:21187:35"/>which are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly vngratefull, and too prodigal.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The daungers of death.</head>
                  <p>THe diuel doth with al his engines and ſnares ſeeke to intrap mans Soule at the very howre of death (if God of his ſpeciall goodneſſe aſſyſte him not) tempting him fyrſte of the verity of his faith, &amp; perſuading him to forgo the ſame, putting him in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, thinking with the greatnes of them to driue him into diſpayre. And at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame inſtaunt, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly a pang more painful then tongue can tel aſſayleth him, which is, the ſeparation of the ſoule from the body. That paine is ſo great, that as then he can remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber nought els but the deadly pa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges of death only. Therfore it is written, <hi>In death (O Lorde) none remembreth thee.</hi> And <hi>Saint Auguſtine</hi> ſayth, The ſinner is ſtricken with ſuch animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity, that dying he forgetteth him ſelfe, who whylſt he lyued remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21187:35"/>not God. <hi>Saint Barnarde</hi> alſo treating of the ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e of death, Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſpyrites (ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>th he) watcheth at my doores, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rrible diuels at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende my comming, ſo that I dare not goe forth. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> lie I am not able to eſcape theyr haudes, vnleſſe the Lorde defende me. But he who tedeemed me wyll defende and faue me.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Howe we ſhoulde comfort thoſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that be in daunger of death.</head>
                  <p>To the end that euery man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>night learne the ryght waye howe to dye, I haue gathered together theſe. ſewe lynes folowing out of dyuers good Authors.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Three exhortations to the ſicke.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Conſider good Brother that all men, of what condition or degree ſoeuer they bee, muſt once dye, ſome ſooner, &amp; ſome later, according to the tyme appoynted them by God, to whom we are al ſubiect (to paye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Nature hir fees) whenſoeuer his
<pb facs="tcp:21187:36"/>omnipotencie ſhal thinke good, who hath appointed this worlde vnto vs as a bayting Inne, and not to be our continual dwelling place. There is no cauſe therefore why you ſhould ſo much affect this tranſitory life, for by how much the lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger your life is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed, by ſo much y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> more your ſyns are increaſed. And y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> elder you grow in age, the more your offences are multiplied for euery day vice increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, and vertue decayeth. We ought therefore to be the more wylling to dye, for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> by flytting from this poore mortal life, we ſhal come to the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting and bleſſed lyfe.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Acknowledge good brother moſt thankfully<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Gods bountiful goodnes towardes thee, in that that hytherto of his vnſpeakeable mercie he hath permitted thee to lyue, yea &amp; for that at this preſent extremitie of death, his hyghneſſe hath graunted thee thy perfect ſenſes, reaſon, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, whereby thou mayſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21187:36"/>thy bounden duety vnto his heauenly Maieſtie. And in that he hath not oppreſſed, not preuented thee with ſodaine death: and for that alſo he hath of his merciful goodnes called thee vnto his true and vnfaig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned faith, through which by his help thou ſhall be brought to his euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting kingdome and eternal inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce. For this and al other his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable benefites, geue vnto his highneſſe moſt hartie thankes, and altogether betake thy ſelfe vnto his endles mercie, humblie crauing par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of him for thine offences.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Conſider that God the Father hath geuen and yeelded his welbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſonne, in whome he tooke great delyght, to be crucifyed and tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with innumerable tribulations, tortures, and paynes, and to ſuffer moſt vyle &amp; bitter death for vs moſt wretched ſinners. Seeing therefore thou haſt in this tranſitorie life com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytted &amp; done innumerable ſynnes
<pb facs="tcp:21187:37"/>and haynous offences, which deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth farre greeuouſer and greater paynes and puniſhmentes then bee aſſigned vnto thee. Thou oughteſt therfore patientlie to beare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paines and panges of this thy deſerued diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe and death.</p>
                  <p>Chriſt for thine offences moſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynglie and patientlie ſuffred death, and the holy Martyrs and Apoſtles with al theyr minde moſte wyllingly imbraced death for his names ſake. Knowe thou therefore, that what maner of death ſoeuer thou ſuffreſt, is muche leſſe painefull then theyrs, for wyl thou, nyl thou, die thou muſt, therefore in the name of Chriſt good brother take it patiently.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Queſtions to bee asked of him that lyeth ſicke, by the Miniſter or any other godly perſon.</head>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1</hi> Wylte thou lyue and dye in the true fayth of Ieſus Chriſte, as a true Chriſtian?</p>
                  <p>I wyl.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="34" facs="tcp:21187:37"/> 
                     <hi>2</hi> Wylt thou aſke forgeuenes of him for all thine offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted againſt his holy maieſty, &amp; for that thou haſt not worthily honoured him?</p>
                  <p>I doo aſke.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3</hi> Haſt thou not determyned with thy ſelfe to alter thy trade of lyfe into a better, if it ſhal pleaſe Gods good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou ſhalt eſcape this diſeaſe?</p>
                  <p>I haue determined.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4</hi> Doſt thou not humblie craue and beſeech him to grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thee grace not to decline from this thy good intent, that thou mayeſt repentauntlye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayle thy former faultes, and that thou mayſt henceforwarde continue in al goodnes?</p>
                  <p>I doo requyre.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5</hi> Doſt thou not hartely forgeue all offences committed againſt thee?</p>
                  <p>I doo forgeue.</p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6</hi> Wylt thou not earneſtly aſke for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuenes of al them whom thou haſt in any wyſe offended?</p>
                  <p>I doo aſke.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:21187:38"/>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> Doſte thou not clearely caſte out of thy hart al enuie, malice, &amp; hatred, whatſoeuer thou beareſt to any cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ature, and willingly be reconciled in perfect charitie to euery man?</p>
                  <p>I am willing.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8</hi> Wilt thou willingly reſtore what ſoeuer thou haſt wrongfully taken or withholden from any man?</p>
                  <p>I wyl.</p>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9</hi> Doſt thou not paciently take in good woorth theſe paynes for the name of God?</p>
                  <p>I doo.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Prayers to be ſayde at the howre of death.</head>
                  <p>INto thy handes (O Lorde) I commende my ſoule, thou haſte redeemed me, O Lorde God of trueth.</p>
                  <p>Ieſus Chriſte the Father of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, make mee one of thy ſeruauntes, helpe mee in my extreme neceſſitie, Succour my needeful and deſolate
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21187:38"/>ſoule, O Lord my god, that it be not deuoured by helhoundes.</p>
                  <p>For the honour and vertue of thy bytter Paſſion, moſt mightie Lorde Ieſus Chriſte, commaunde that my name may bee regiſtred among the number of thine elect.</p>
                  <p>O my Creator &amp; redeemer Ieſus Chriſte, I yeelde my ſelfe vnto thee, forſake me not, be holde I flye vnto thee, ſuccor me, and reproue me not.</p>
                  <p>O Lorde Ieſus Chriſte the ſonne of the liuing God, put thy Paſſion, Croſſe and death, betwixt my ſoule and thy iudgement.</p>
                  <p>Nowe, O Lorde, according vnto thy wyl haue mercy vppon mee, and commaunde that my ſoule be recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued into thy peace.</p>
                  <p>Let that ſweete voyce, O Lorde, ſound in the eares of my ſoule, This day thou ſhalt be with mee in Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21187:39"/>
                  <head>The maner howe Howe to foreſee that thinges goe rightly with anye when he dyeth.</head>
                  <p>IF the ſicke man doe wauer, ſtray, or doubt any thing of the veritie of his fayth, put him in remembraunce of the Apoſtles and holy Martyrs, which for the defence of this true fayth haue ſuffered all kindes of tormentes and paines.</p>
                  <p>If hee be in diſpayre, then tell him, that although his offences bee neuer ſo great and many, yet the goodnes of our mercyful Lord is much more, for his mercies do exceede the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie of all our effences, which hee of his goodnes offereth in common to euery man, leſt hee himſelfe doe wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully refuſe the ſame: for his mercye is infinite and without number. Al the offences that euer were commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſince the beginning of the worlde may be numbred, al which are clerly waſhed awaye with the leaſt drop of the blood of our lord Ieſus Chriſt,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21187:39"/>which he ſhed at the time of his byt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter paſſion. Our Lorde God of his great clemencie was redy to cal vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his mercy <hi>Iudas,</hi> the wickedſt man that euer lyued, when he ſayde vnto him, My freende. Yet for that he dyd diſpayre, he was condemned, and ſo ſinned more by falling into diſpayre, then by betraying of his maiſter our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, the immacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late Lambe, and onely begotten ſonne of God the Father. And laſtlye put in thy minde, that the forgiuenes of ſinnes is an Article of our faith, by which is ſignified vnto vs, that how often and howe greeuous ſoeuer our offences are, yee by true repentance of our ſinnes yet ſhal obteine true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion for them: wherof, whoſoeuer doubteth, he is no true Chriſtian.</p>
                  <p>If you ſee that hee do not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently yelde vp the Ghoſt, then reade to him the hyſtorie of the Paſſion, or ſome other good and Godly hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie (wherein hee delighted moſt
<pb facs="tcp:21187:40"/>when he was in health (or the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes of God, to the ende that hee maye with more perfectnes repent him ſelfe, if hee haue oughte committed agaynſt them,</p>
                  <p>If for lacke of ſpeache hee bee not able to aunſwere with woordes, then let hym aunſwere in mynde, and with outwarde ſignes expreſſe his conſcience, for they are (through Gods mercye) ſufficient to obteyne grace.</p>
                  <p>Put him no wiſe in remembraunce of his wife, children, freends, or tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral wealth, vnleſſe it bee neceſſary for his ſpiritual health:</p>
                  <p>Put him not in ouermuche hope of bodyly health, leſt by that meanes he might withdraw his minde from the ſpirituall care that hee hath of his ſoule: For by the health of the ſoule hee ſhoulde ſeeke for the health of the bodye, onelye requiringe it at Gods hande, if his goodneſſe ſhall thinke it moſt meete and beſte for his
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21187:40"/>ſoule. For God is a furtherer of the pacient and wel diſpoſed, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral diſeaſes bring for the moſte parte langour and grefe to the ſoule. We ſhould therefore firſt prouide for our ſoule, and repent vs of our ſinnes, before we take any care of our bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly health.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Heereafter followeth a breefe Dialogue touching the day of Iudgement. Betweene Raymundus, and Dominicus.</head>
                  <p>I Haue (my <hi>Raymundus</hi>) all this long time ſince our laſte com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication bene very deſirous to knowe howe our mercyful Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chryſt wyl in thende rewarde euery man. Wherefore I praye you of your curteſie ſhew me ſomewhat touching this poynte. <hi>Raym:</hi> My
<pb facs="tcp:21187:41"/>freende <hi>Dominicus,</hi> I graunte to thy requeſt, for it is not conueniente that we leaue man (of whom hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to wee haue conferred) vnfiniſhed. Seeing wee haue treated of hys creation, and ſeeing wee haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of hys reparation: wee wyll nowe talke ſomewhat touchinge his final iudgement. God worketh three wayes concerning man, that is to ſaye, in creation, reformation, and in iudging him moſte iuſtlye ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his workes. Seeing then man is the liuely and magnificente worke of God, and aboue al crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures moſte lyke vnto his Maker, he oughte not therefore to bee leſte vnfiniſhed and vnpertected. And for that he can not come to the verie laſte ende of perfection before his life bee examined and iudged, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the quality of it hee maye receyue rewarde at the laſt retribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, eyther to eternal payne, or to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting glory. Therefore it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21187:41"/>to conferre in few wordes, of this laſt and general iudgement, and by certaine natural reaſons to ſhew taa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is to come. <hi>Domi.</hi> I beſeech you ſo to do, for I am determined with al my hart to heare you. <hi>Raym.</hi> We wil proue that the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is to come, by the very nature of ioy &amp; gladneſſe them ſelues. It muſt needes be, that the iuſt manne for his iuſtice ſhal ſo magnifycently reioyce, that he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reioyce more perfectly. And that the wickedman for his iniquitie be caſt into heauineſſe, as there may be no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>reater. And that this may be do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, the general iudgement muſt of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> be pronou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ced, wherin good men may receiue al gladneſſe and be praiſed of all men: and Reprobates condemned of all men, maye receiue eternall heauineſſe. There are but two things iudicable, that is, a good life, and an euill life. And for that contrary things being put together, each of them geueth better light to
<pb facs="tcp:21187:42"/>the other. Therfore the general ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is to come, wherin the good in compariſon of the euil, ſhal moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crouſly ſhine. And the euil in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon of the good, ſhal be contamina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with vtter confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>Domi.</hi> This which you ſay is terrible, and ought to moue the hartes of wicked men. But is this the laſt retribution of al, or ſhall this be done to the ſoule of man onelye, or vnto it altoge alther with the fleſh.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The general iudgement of the dead re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth an vniuerſall reſurrection.</head>
                  <p>RAym. I haue ſaide in the fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mer Chapter, that the generall iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment appertaineth to mankind, and to humaine nature belongeth both a body &amp; ſoule. For as there is a cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall nature and a ſpiritual nature diſtinetly: ſo there is a corporall and a ſpirituall nature vnited. And for that this nature is both iuditable &amp; rewardable: it is therfore neceſſary that it be iudged both in bodye and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21187:42"/>ſoule. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this may be done, there muſt be a reſurrection of al bodies, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> as the foule with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body, &amp; in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, hath eyther ſinned or done iuſtly: ſo it may like wiſe with the body re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue that that is adioyned vnto it. And becauſe that this laſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is the fynal retribution of all bodies, there muſt therfore be a generall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of all the deade, and the vniuerſall iudgement and the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dead are inſeperably lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked together in one chaine. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, the reſurrection of the deade is neceſſary for the accompliſhment of al. The very children which of them ſelues haue not offended, for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complyſhment of all, muſt needes riſe with others.</p>
                  <p>Furthermore, eyther none, or all ſhall ryſe againe: But Chriſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man already from death hath ry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen: Therefore all men ſhall ryſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne. For reſurrection is incident to humaine nature. Neyther is it
<pb facs="tcp:21187:43"/>impoſſible to do that thing which is once done. As a graine of come fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling into the earth, being dead and growing againe, bryngeth fruicte manyfolde: So Chriſt beeing dead and ryſen agayne, worketh an in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable reſurrection of bodies.</p>
                  <p>As that reſurrection was not wrought in Chriſt by vertue of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity: ſo neither ſhal it be wrought in vs, out by power diuine. The vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfull men thinke that God is not able to raiſe vp liuing fleſhe out of dead conſumed aſhes. As God was able to bring foorth innumerable kindes of thinges out of the earth at one: ſo may hee now eaſilye rayſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine the ſame bodies which alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy hath bene, out of their own aſhes. As the iuſtice of God requireth the ſame, ſo the maieſty of his vertue is able to do the ſame. Moreouer, ſeing God was able to make ſo many bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies which were not at all, is he not like wiſe able to repaire the bodies
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:21187:43"/>which are periſhed? Furthermore, if God hath with his mightys hande made ſome incorruptible: bodies whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fore then ſhould he not be able to repaire our corporall bodies, and to make the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ortal?</p>
                  <p>I think I ſhal greatly further thee, if I can by reaſon of the power and honour of God, proue the geuerall iudgement to come. For ſeeing that God of his owne free will, without the requeſt or compulſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of any hath created humaine nature, when there was none: and ſeeing the finall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution is a worke to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> honor one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of God, proceding from himſelfe, &amp; whatſoeuer God worketh of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: he worketh the ſame to his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>on honor, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> uſe the iudgement of this ſmall retribution is the laſt and perfect worke of God touching man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde: God wil openly w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ke therin, by manifeſting the great power and honor of his wiſedome, &amp; of his iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ice. His power ſhal appeare in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb facs="tcp:21187:44"/>of many bodies, his wiſedome in examining of conſciences, and his iuſtice in beſtowing rewards. This iudgement requireth an vprightnes to be ſhewed in the Iudge, authority of excellent maieſty in his irreuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſentences, and fulneſſe of iuſtice &amp; goodneſſe in beſtowing of gifts, or of puniſhmentes. Seeing alſo this Iudgement is of great honor &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, it is requiſite that it be done w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> great ſolemnity and magnifycence, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Thrones and powers ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing theyr attendaunce. It becommeth ſuch a Iudge to vſe in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e maieſty: and it behoueth this Iudical power, that God do appeare and ſhewe him ſelfe to al <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a dreadful threatning, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> fearful Iudge, and that h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>orth this terror according to his e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>erent Maieſty. All ſafety wylbe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>for the iuſt, and yet they will receiue him with great vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and reuerence, in beholding his moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Manſty, his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:21187:44"/>vertue, and dignity. As this worke of iudgement is the laſt of all workes: ſo likewiſe the ſame will he aboue all his handye, workes, moſt pure, moſt excellent, moſt ſolemne, and moſt honorable.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Domi.</hi> But who is he that ſhall be the Iudge of all? I knowe it is God, but is it God verye man, that ſhal be both Iudge and rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, which fyrſt was the repayrer of all? <hi>Raym.</hi> Euen the ſame Ieſus Chriſt the onely Sonne of God, to whome the Father hath geuen all Iudgement, for that he is the Son of man, he ſhall iudge man, ſeeing he is man, the repayrer &amp; redemer of man.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Of the excellencie of this day aboue all other dayes.</head>
                  <p>I Wyl ſay ſome what of the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificency of the laſt day. In this day the workes of all the dayes before ſhall be gathered togeather, and ſhall receiue their rewarde. In this day God wil worke more mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiently
<pb facs="tcp:21187:45"/>then he hath wrought in other dayes, as in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ayſing the be dead, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>inor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>an, and in rewarding ther<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>h eternall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards. In this day God worketh, &amp; in the other daies men haue wrou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght al their works: In this day God will ſhew the workes of his power, will do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ice, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eritie and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, compleeting all his workes in moſt hieſt renown<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e glory &amp; honor. This day wil be the day of feare, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ions, &amp; dread vnto the wicked, but a day of ioy &amp; glory vnto the iuſt and goodman. This day ought to be alwaies in our remembraunce. And we ought to direct the workes of all our daies vnto this day, and to geue our ſelues ſo far forth as we may vnto iuſtice &amp; vertue, leaſt at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day before ſo great a Iudge, and in the light and meeting of all men and Angelles, we be confounded. Where as there is no memorye of this day, there remaineth inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtancie, malice,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21187:45"/>and al wicked and peruerſe workes.</p>
                  <p>And becauſe that this moſt magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficent Iudge cannot erre, neither be corrupted nor deceaued, for that he ſearcheth the reines and harts of all men, who ſeeth althinges &amp; neglec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth nothing Therfore remembring theſe things alwaies, &amp; putting this day before our eyes, we ought to do that which is good. <hi>Raim.</hi> We haue gathered out of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which you haue ſaide, that there ſhalbe a perpetual ſeperation of the good and the euil, thone fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thother. Thoſe which haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> themſelues to <hi>Lucifer.</hi> his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked will, makings themſelues his members, ſhalbe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him condemned to euerlaſting fyre. And thoſe which haue folowed Chriſt our lord, ſhalbe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp to euerlaſting glory.</p>
                  <p>The reprobates ſhalbe plunged in a moſte deepe bottomleſſe pitte: and the choſen ſhalbe lifted vp to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt heauen. They ſhalbe geuen to the fyre, and thoſe to pleaſures. They
<pb facs="tcp:21187:46"/>ſhall haue deuils to their fellowes, &amp; theſe ſhalbe accompanied with An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels. They for extreme tribulation ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ace, &amp; theſe for the greatnes of their ioyes ſhal geue harty tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ks. A moſt thicke and eternall darkenes ſhalbe alwaies caſt vpon them, &amp; to theſe God ſhalbe an euerlaſtinge light, &amp; the lambe ſhalbe their light.</p>
                  <p>Now you haue that which you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired. Gather therefore by theſe the full and laſt finiſhing of man: for if he be adiudged good, the beſt of all ſhalbe allotted vnto him, that is, to be with Angels in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdom of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: But if he be adiudged euil: then ſhal he continually poſſeſſe the worſt place of all with the deuils in Hel.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dom.</hi> Nowe, ſeeing that I am come to thende of all theſe thinges which I ſought for, and to the very laſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution, I geue you moſte hartye thankes, for that you haue vouched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to graunt to my requeſte, and for your laboure and induſtry, whereby
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21187:46"/>you haue moſt effectually inſtructed me, duringe my lyfe, I wil alwayes reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber this moſt wholſom inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, remembringe my ſelfe to bee made by my redeemer, and farre ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted aboue other creatures. And I being through mine owne pride and diſobedience, ſlidden and falne down &amp; with a thouſand other calamities intercepted, am redeemed &amp; reſtored againe by Chriſt hauing compaſſion vpon me, and by him reſerued to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue eternall rewarde.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The thirde thinge worthy to be remembred is, the payns of hel.</head>
                  <p>CHriſte hath his fan in his hand, &amp; he v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> his barn flower, and gather his wheat corne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame: and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> burne the chaffe with vnquenchable fyre.</p>
                  <p>By the fanne of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, is vnderſtoode his iudiciall power and iuſt iudgement. And by this Barne flower is vnderſtoode
<pb facs="tcp:21187:47"/>the Churche, or humaine kinde: By the Wheate is ſignified his ele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>te: By the Cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e the reprobates: &amp; by the Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e is vnderſtoode the kings dome releſtiall. The ſence of theſe wordes is, that as by the Fame the corne is made cleane, &amp; as the chaſt, is women away, &amp; the corne left? ſo the ſon of God wil purge his church, wherein (amongeſt the choſen &amp; the iuſt) the reprobates, and wickedare mingled: but in the day of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t they ſhalbe ſeuered one fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another, in place &amp; rewards, as now they dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in conuerſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The vngodly are rightly called the chaff, becauſe they are vaine &amp; light &amp; follow the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their mindes. The vertuous are compared to the wheat, for they are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruite of Chriſt, borne in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> field of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, regenerate of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and the holy ghoſt ſpiritually, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in charitye, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t with diuine grace &amp; heauenlye giftes. They are tranſferred from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> barn flower of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:21187:47"/>Church militant vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> barne of the triumphant church. And the wicked being the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Babilon (which is of confuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) they are hurled head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long into a fornace of burning fyre, and eternall damnation.</p>
                  <p>And for y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hetherto we haue trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of death &amp; iudgement, I mene to ſet forth a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>dowe of the paynes of hel, whereby the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly Ieruſalem maye appence the excellenter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Of Hell.</head>
                  <p>WHoe is able to expreſſe the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes appointed for the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly and euill liuers, in that deadly place called Hel? What other thinge can be there but continual flames of fyre, eternal tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; infinite ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities of al euils? Burning flouds that run from ſtinking fens fil vp all places therein. There dwelleth wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked and vglye Angels, headed and winged like dragons, with flaming eyes, caſting of fierye dartes, whoſe teeth are more long &amp; ſharpe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the
<pb facs="tcp:21187:48"/>Elephants, wherwithal they pinch, gnaw, and torment, more greeuous the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doeth the Dragons taile, whoſe lookes bringeth ſodaine feare, gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous paynes, and feareful death.</p>
                  <p>Oh, I woulde to God that death might ende theſe painefull extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. But alas, ſe yet another torture greuouſer then this: The ſoule ſhal ſtil liue, &amp; he alwayes vnder the rule &amp; gouernance of cruel tormentors: And further, beinge gnawen with Serpentes, changinge their holdes, they do with new bitinges a freſhe from time to time torment and tears y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoule in peeces. Dragons ſhal ther deuoure the lips of the blaſphemers, &amp; the Cockatrice with greedy teeth ſhal ſunder &amp; teare in peeces y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of the wicked. Al kinde of horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble beaſtes wil there torment w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ceaſſing, the ſoules of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miſbeleues. Howling &amp; be wailing, lamentation &amp; rearing do ther continually ſound, fearful ſcriches, and confuſed cries
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:21187:48"/>are there in al places ſodenly rayſed. Which crye is procured by the cruel force of tortures, and is thruſte forth by the ſtrength of burninge flames. The ſame tribulations whervnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſoules are receued be without al end and meaſure. For the ſoules are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually conſumed with the broiling heate of fierye flames, and beeing throughly burned, are againe and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine tormented in new kindled fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. There are wormes that neuer dye, fire that neuer quencheth, and continuall gnaſhing of teeth.</p>
                  <p>There is in hell deadly colde, conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Iſe, cruel hunger, vnme aſura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thirſte, perpetual ſorowe, raging peſtilence, vnceaſſable puniſhments, continual darkeneſſe, and nightes of horrible obſcurenes. The miſerable ſoule findeth there no reſt, but is tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with al kinde of tormentes. There is mortall death, defectiue lacke, &amp; endleſſe ende. What faythful man can then but tremble to heare
<pb facs="tcp:21187:49"/>and knowe of ſuch paynes.</p>
                  <p>Deliuer vs we beſeeche thee good Lorde from that lake of miſerie. ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure place, and darke world couered with the deadlye cloude of death, wher no order is obſerued, but an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtinge horronre, Stir vp oure hartes, moſte merciful God, vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true fruites of repentance. We hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blye beſeeche thy Maieſty, to deliuer vs from theſe eternal paines.</p>
                  <p>See here, how great, how in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable, how vnmeaſurable, &amp; how perpetual, the miſeries, paines &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felicities of the condemned are. He which wil not be terrified by theſe deſcriptions is blind &amp; hard harted, neither hath he anye ſpiritual ſence, but is rather altogether deade: Let him notwithſtandinge looke aboute him, and riſe from the depth of his ſinne, lifting vp the eyes of his hart, to conſider theſe thinges.</p>
                  <p>And euerye man which as yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteth in ſinne, let him impreſſe the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21187:49"/>conſideration of theſe thinges in his minde, that at the leaſt, by the horror of them, hee maye bee withdrawen from vice, and directed to vertue.</p>
                  <p>He alſo which already hath begun to enter into the way of vertue, let him by the due conſideration of theſe thinges caſt off all vnſtableneſſe and vnbeliefe. And let al true beleeue us caſt out and vomite foorth with hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and hatefulnes, all the delectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the fleſhe, and van<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ties of the world, through which they come to ſo great calamities in hell.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ Hereafter followeth cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne meditations of the Heauenlye kingdome or the ioyes of Heauen.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E oughte ſo to liue in this worlde, that when our bodies beginne to become ſubiectes to wormes in the Sepulture, then our ſoules ſhould beginne to be glad with Saintes in
<pb facs="tcp:21187:50"/>heauen, directing of ſpyrites thither whither it continually aſpyreth. We ought to haſten our ſelues thither, where wee ſhall alwayes lyue, and where we ſhalle are death no more. If we do any thing at al affect this v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ding and tranſitory life, which at no time is void of cares and labors: and that by eating, drinking, ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, or any other recreation, ſcarce can we at any time ſatiſly the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of the fleſh.</p>
                  <p>By how much the more ought we to deſyre and wiſhe for eternal life, wherein we ſhal abide nor ſuffer no lobor or payne, where there is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual health, eternal felicity, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py lyberty and perfect blyſſe, where men ſhalbe like vnto the Angels of God, and iuſt men ſhal ſhine as the Sun, in the kingdom of their father.</p>
                  <p>How thinkeſt thou then? of what brightnes wil the ſoule be, when the body ſhal poſſeſſe the light of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sun? In that place there is no heauineſſe,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21187:50"/>no ſorrow, no griefe, no feare no la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor, no death, but a perpetual health and euerlaſting bliſſe.</p>
                  <p>In which eternal kingdome, there is no malice nor miſery of the fleſhe, no diſeaſe, no lack, no hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger, no thriſt no colde nor heate, no weri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es of faſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting nor temptation of the enemy, no will to ſinne, nor power to do euyl, but a quiet harborough of pleaſur &amp; crumph, where men in the ſociety of Angels ſhal continually dwel with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any infyrmity of the fleſh.</p>
                  <p>There is infinite ioy, eternal bliſſe, from whence none ſhalbe remoued that once can enter therein. Ther is the reſt from labours, peace fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the enemy, a new kinde of pleaſure, a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie of eternity, taking a meruai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ldus delite and exceeding pleſure, in the beholding of God. Who is he the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that wil not ſeeke and deſyre by all means poſſible to be a dweller there both for the deſire of peace, ioye, and eternity, &amp; for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perfect ſight of god?</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <pb facs="tcp:21187:51"/>
                  <head>The deſire the ſoule hath to the Heauenly iudgement.</head>
                  <p>O Spirituall Hieruſalem the holye citie of God, happy wer my ſoule, if I might obteine to behold thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, thy gates, thy wale thy ſtreetes, thy innumerable habitations, thy moſt noble citizens, and thy omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent king, in his maieſty &amp; glory.</p>
                  <p>For thy walles are made of preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſtones, thy gates of excellent margarites, thy ſtretes of moſt pure golde, wherein that ſweete ſong <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leluy a</hi> is inceſſantly ſonge. Thy ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifolde manſions are founded vpon ſquare ſtones, and builded with S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyres, couered with golden Tiles, wherin no wicked man entreth, nor ſinner dwelleth. O heauenly Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, thou art ſweete &amp; bewtiful in al thy peaſures and delights. There are no ſuch miſeries in thee, as wee feele, abid &amp; ſuffer in this poore &amp; mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable life. Ther is in thee no dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, no night, nor chaunge of time.</p>
                  <p>The ſhining of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Moon, the twink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21187:51"/>brightneſſe of the ſtars geueth not light in thee, but only the God of God, the light of light, and the Sun of iuſtice geueth light in thee. The white &amp; inunaculate Lambe, a moſt beutiful light is thy light: thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>right<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes &amp; goodnes is an endles contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation and beholding of thy moſte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ewtiful king? The king of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ngs is in the middeſt of thee, in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> on ech <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> with his beloued <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>. In thee are legions of Angels ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ging of ſweete <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>es, in thee are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> felow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip of heauenly Citizens, there reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſweete ſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nity of al ſuch as returne from this miſerable pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage vnto thy glory, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prouident co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of the prophetes dwel in thee, there are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bet of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> twelue Apoſtles, and there is the victorious army of innumerable martirs, there are true, perfect &amp; holy men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, which haue vanquiſhed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, and the infirmity of the fleſh. Ther are yong childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and
<pb facs="tcp:21187:52"/>maide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which haue paſſed ouer their yeres in holines of life, ther are they that haue eſcaped y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſnares &amp; nets of pleaſure and ſenſuality: Euerye one reioiceth in his degree, though not e<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>qual in glorye, yet lyke in ioyes and gladnes: For there reigneth perfect charity; and God is al in al, whom without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually, and ſtil in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>olding him theyr loue incre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth, they loue &amp; pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſe him al theyr wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> to the prayſe of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ende intermiſſion, or labour.</p>
                  <p>Happye were I, yea, moſt happye, if I could obteine after my departure from this life, to beare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſong of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly melody, which is ſong by theſe heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly Citizens, &amp; happy companies of bleſſed ſpirites in the laud &amp; praiſe of the eternal king. Moſt fortunate and bleſſed wer I, if I my ſelfe could come to ſing that ſweete ſong, and to ſtand neere my kinge, my God and captain, &amp; to behold him in his glory and maieſty, as he himſelf hath vou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chedſafe
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21187:52"/>to promiſe, ſaying: father I wil that thoſe which thou haſt geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me, be with me, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they may ſee that excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t purenes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue with thee, before the conſtitution of the world. Let him who miniſtreth vnto me, fol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowe me, &amp; where I am <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t be. And again: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e that loueth me, is beloued of my father, &amp; I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>il loue him, and ſhew my ſelf vnto him.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Howe plentifull of al goodnes, and how ſpare of all euill, the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Hieruſalem is.</head>
                  <p>O My ſoule, let vs returne vnto the heauenly citie, wherin we are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtred &amp; appointed to be dwellers, as the felowes of Saints, and houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde ſeruances of our Lord, heires of God, and coheires with Chriſte our Sauiour. Let vs conſider ſo far as poſſible we can, of theſe licitye of that holy Citie, ſaying with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete, O what glorious thinges are ſayde of thee (O thou Citie of God) for thou art the habitacle of al thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:21187:53"/>that reioice and be glad. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> art fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with ioye. There is no olde age, nor miſerye of age in thee. There is none maimed, lame, crookebact, nor deformed in thee, for in thee al men grow to ful ſtrength and perfectnes, yea, vnto the very yeres of our Saui or Chriſt. What life is happier then that life, where there is no feare of pouerty, nor weakeneſſe by deſeaſe. Ther is no anger, hurt nor enuy, no couetouſnes nor ambitious aſpiring to honor, nor power, pricketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mind of any that dwel in that holy Citie. The feare of the deuil &amp; his dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers, and the terror of hel is far abſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee. The death neither of body nor ſoule is feared in thee: but a pleaſant life rewarded with in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ortalitye. Ther wil be then no euil; peace ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be there proclaymed in euery place, and al diſcorde ſhalbe quyte forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: for the concorde of the holye Saintes is one. Althinges ſhalbe repie at with peace and gladnes, tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quilitie,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:21187:53"/>reſt, and a continual excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent brightnes, farre vnlike to this whiche nowe we ſee: Adn by howe much the better ech one liued in this world, he ſhal in that world be by ſo much the more the cleerer. For it is read, that that Citie needeth not the light of the Sun nor of the Moone, for there the Lambe is their lampe, and the omnipotent Lorde geueth them light. There Saintes doſh me like Starres in perpetual eternitie, as the pureneſſe of the heauens that geueth light to many.</p>
                  <p>Wherfore, ther is no night nor dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, there is no contracy meeting of clowdes, no extremity of coulde nor heat, but a wonderful temperatenes of al things, which no eie can ſee, no eare ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heare, nor heart imagine, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing only thoſe who enioy the ſame, whoſe names are writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> booke of life. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which excelleth this, is the felowſhip of Angels, Archa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gels, and al the vertues of heauen. To be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb facs="tcp:21187:54"/>the Apoſtles, Martirs and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes, and to ſee our forefathers, al theſe are glorious. But, to behold y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perfect countenaunce of God and to ſee his incomprehenſible lighte, is a far excellenter glorie. For when we ſhall ſee God in himſelf, then ſhal we ſee &amp; haue in our ſelues that which continuallye without ende we ſhall contemplate and beholde.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ A ſuppoſed deſcription of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Hieruſalem.</head>
                  <p>O Beloued countrey, O heuenly ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, what can be ſufficiently writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or beleued of thee, for that in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e is that goodnes, ioy and ſolace, that eyes ſee not, that eares here not, nor minde of man can ſo-muche as once coniecture, for which ſo many Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Martirs haue moſte willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffered death. Thy gates do gliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtones moſt precious, thy ſtreetes are paued with burni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed golde, thy walles are made of moſt precious ſtones, in thee are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21187:54"/>pleaſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t gardens, alwaies greener then the fields of Theſſalie, wherin freſh flowres, &amp; dainty vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> do continually bud &amp; grow. In thee vnſpeakeable ſweete odours of Cinamon &amp; Balme do alwaies ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly breath and ſmel. The beautie of althings do increaſe in thee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ke, remaine without fading, abide without corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; without chaunge do eternally continue. In thee is al temperatenes &amp; purenes of ayre, farre exceeding the capacitie of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. In thee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>peace &amp; reſt ſurpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng meaſure. In thee is euerlaſting day, &amp; one ſpirit of althings. In thee is certain aſſurance, aſſured eternity eternal quietnes quiet happines, hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>py pleaſure, &amp; pleaſaunt mirth. Iuſt men do ſhine in thee as the ſun. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be wiſhed, loued or ſought for, but it is in thee to be founde, &amp; in thee one lye is conteined y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which no wher els can be had. O what glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out offence, what flouds of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere pleſure, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> bottomles pleſure of
<pb facs="tcp:21187:55"/>ſweete delectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is it, to behold the God of Gods in Sion, to looke vpon the inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehenſible glory of the holy trinity, &amp; to taſte of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perfect ſweece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, from which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth al goodnes to humaine kinde? What a pleaſure is it to behold the maieſtly of God, to be in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perpetual company of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed troupes of Angels, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Apoſtles and Martirs, with holy and bleſſed virgins, to know al the Citizens of heauen, and alwaye to reioyce in eternal felicitie? O my ſoule, loue this bleſſed palace, and in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wardly affect the ſame, which with fleſhly eyes cannot be ſeene, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the eies of thy faith. Beleeue that which thou ſeeſt not, to the ende that thou maieſt ſometime obteine that which thou beleeueſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Of the perfect and abſolute ioy of eternall lyfe.</head>
                  <p>MY God, my Lord, my heartes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyght, tel vnto my ſoule, if this be the ioy that thou haſt ſpoken of vnto
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21187:55"/>vs by thy ſonne. For y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſaideſt: Aſke, &amp; you ſhal haue, to the ende that your ioies may be perfect. I haue found a certaine kinde of ioy, yea, more then perfect: &amp; yet, although man hath a perfect hart, a perfect mind, a perfect ſoule, and that man is al repleniſhed with ioy. There reſteth yet another ioy, that aboue meaſure paſſeth this, for al ioyes: cannot be contemed in him that reioyſeth, but al thoſe that reioyce, ſhal emer in the ioye of our Lord. (But truely that ioy, wherein thine elect reioyce, cannot bee ſeene, heard, nor be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſed within the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity of man.) Therfore, O Lord, in al theſe my ſayinges, I haue not ſo much as once thought vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any part of the ioyes of thine elect. They ſhal in al places ſo much reioyce as they loued thee: and ſo much loue thee, as they acknowledge thee their Lorde. No eie ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſee, no toung ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tel, no eare can heare, nor hart can think (in this life) how much they acknowledge &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:21187:56"/>loue thee in the life to come. I beſech thee O Lord, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may loue thee &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in thee. And though I cannot come to that perfectne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in this lyfe, yet graunt, that I may from day to day ſo increaſe therein, that I maye after this life, come to the ful perfect<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes thereof. Let me ſo profite in this knowledge, that in time to come I maye be perfectly inſtructed therin. Let thy loue good Lord, ſo increaſe &amp; grow in me that I may be therin perfectly grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in the life to come. Graunt, I beſeech thee, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I maye ſo reioyce in hope, as that I maye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly reioice in ioy after this world. O true &amp; euerliuing God, graunt, I beſeeche thee, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may receaue that which thou haſt promiſe dme, that is that my ioye maye be perfecte in the world of worlds, &amp; that in the meane time, my minde may reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame my tongue may ſpeak therof, my hart may loue it, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> my mouth may talk thereof. Let my ſoule hunger for it,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:21187:56"/>my fleſh deſyre it, and all my bodilye ſubſtaunce feruentlye require it, tyl ſuch time as I do enter into the ioies of my Lord my God, where I ſhal remaine for euer.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>A prayer whereby thou maieſt be ſtirred vp vnto the deſire of heauenly thinges.</head>
                  <p>O My God, O the ſweete life of my ſoule, O my true health, O my ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uation, O my onely, eternal, vnchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geable, and chiefeſt goodnes, what other thing beſydes thee ought I to looke or aſke fore What, haue I not al thinges, if I do poſſeſſe thee, who haſt created al things? There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of anye eſtimation, but onelye ſuch thinges as thou haſt made. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the bewty of the Aungels, of bleſſed ſoules, of mortal bodies, of brutiſh beaſtes, the brightnes of the heauens, Statees, Sunne, Fyre, and Ayre, the Sea, Earth, Planets, the flowers, precious ſtones, metals and colours, ſweetenes of al ſoundes
<pb facs="tcp:21187:57"/>and odours, and the delicate taſte of al ſweete thinges proceedeth onely fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee, O Lord. Whatſoeuer grace of comlines, pleſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tnes, ſinenes, ſweet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, vertue, dignity, or ritches, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth in any creature, the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from thee, O God, and al thinges aboundantly flowe in thee without any lacke.</p>
                  <p>Thou art the chiefeſt bewty, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt pleaſure, &amp; chiefeſt deſyre. Thou moſt abu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dantly doſt conteine in thee al bewty, goodneſſe and pleaſure al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies greene &amp; floriſhing, &amp; al good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is far more excellent in thee, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may ſee or proue in any of thy cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>atures. O Creator moſt excellent, y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> art y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pleaſure of althings, thou art the abundantfulnes of perfect ioy, &amp; the vnmeſurable ſea of holy delights &amp; pleaſures, thou art y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> light of incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible cleerenes &amp; paſſing brightnes, O be wtiful, eternal, &amp; incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible light. That which they do ſee, heare, taſte, ſmell, or feele, which are
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21187:57"/>inwardly ioyned vnto thee, through exceeding puceneſſe of hear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> (wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ſt they yet remain in this preſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>) can with no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ouing be expreſſed. The louing imbracementes, the daintye kiſſes of the moth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, wherwith ſhe appeaſeth the weep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g of her ton<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t childe, no, nor the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> wordes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> pleaſant counten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nce of the h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> towar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> loui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> wiſe, are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſhadowes and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ue in reſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t and con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f the ſweete im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>em<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tes, wherewith thou, O Lorde, doſt a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oue thee. But if poore baniſhed men can be ſo bleſſed and happy, and that they can ſee ſuch inexplicable &amp; incomparable goodneſſe, whoe ſee thee but in a darke, had owed glaſſe: how much more happyer then ought we to iudge of thy holy citizens who ſee thee face to face, from whom flow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth riuers of pleaſure more ſweeter then honey, who are perfectly vnited vnto thee, drowned in a bottomeleſſe
<pb facs="tcp:21187:58"/>of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ternal delightes. Thoſe thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>lbelo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ldren doo nowe moſt n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ifeſtly knowe and in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſe lues di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſeſt lyefe ele howe muche (O me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ciful father) thou doſt fau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ur and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> them: and from the be giuning haſte lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>d them. Thou, O Lorde, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rofie willingly, ſinner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eſt and belpeſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ema<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ighten al menne moſte pleaſaun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lye with the light of thy brigh t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Thou doſt comi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly moſte ſam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y and offe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ally, talke in thefeoreete ho we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of euery man. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ddeſt drawe the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tes and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of al men vnto thee with an in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>morehenſible ſweet mes and feruert affe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tion of charitye.</p>
                  <p>Thou doſt qualify, gladden; refreſhe, and fatiſſye, with a delicate deſyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>f enioying thy companye, the he artes and willes of all men. And to ſaye al, O eternal God, thou art all in al, in that moſte holy Citie of newe Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem. That is the happy day, and the ſinguler day, the onely true daie,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:21187:58"/>whereof thou, O Lorde Ieſus, haſte thus ſpoken vnto thy diſciples. (In that day you ſhal knowe that I am in my father, and you in me, and I in you.) O daye ſo much wiſhed for, with moſt harty deſire, wherein the holy ſoules ſhalbe vnited vnto thee, O God, and ſhalbe inſpyred with a meruailous light of wiſedome, and tranſformed into the brightnes of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal glory. O Ieſus, graunt, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeche thee, that ſo longe as I am in the darkeneſſe of this perigrination, that the eyes of my minde maye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde and contemplate the moſt ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning light and brightneſſe of thee, O God, and that I may alwaies pleaſe thee my Lord and God.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Man wiſheth for tribulations of this worlde, to the ende, that he may the more earneſtly deſire the kingdome of heauen.</head>
                  <p>O My ſoule, if wee muſt euery daye ſuffer torments, yea, and a longe
<pb facs="tcp:21187:59"/>time abyde the vexations of this worlde, to the ende that wee myght ſee Chriſt in his glory, and be ioyned in the felowſhip of his Saintes? Is it not conuenient that we ſhould pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientlye ſuffer al kynde of paines, to thende that we myght be partakers of ſo great goodneſſe and glory? Let wicked ſpirites prepare theyr ſnares and temptations, let ſickeneſſe wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the bodye, let apparel trouble the fleſhe, lette laboures oppreſſe it, lette longe wakinges fore watche it, let this manne exclaime againſt me, let that manne diſturbe me, let colde benumme me, let heate burne me, let my conſcience prycke me, let the head ake, let the heart broyle, let the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mack be ouercome with ſuperfluous humors, let the viſage waxe pale and wanne, let al the body be weakned, let my lyfe be ended in ſorowe, let my yeres be conſumed in ſighes, let cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption enter into my bones, and let my bowels guſhe out vnder me:
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21187:59"/>What care I though al theſe come to paſſe, ſo that I may in thende and day of trybulation, come to reſte, and aſcende into the felowſhippe of thoſe that are already preferred vnto glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. How great wil the glorye of the iuſt be, what exceeding gladueſſe wil be amongſt them, when theyr faces ſhal ſhine as the Sunne, and the Lorde in the kingdome of his father beginneth to place his people, eache one in his degree, and rewardeth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye one according to his merytes, geuyng them in ſteede of carthly thinges, heauenly goodneſſe: for tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral thinges, eternal rewards: and for ſmal things, great &amp; ample gifts. Truely, it wyl be a heape of felicity, when the Lord ſhal lead his Saints into the glory of his father, and cauſe them to ſit in celeſtial ſeates, where God is al in al. O what a pleaſaunt happines is it to ſee the Saintes, to be with Saintes, and to be Saintes our ſelues, to ſee God, and to enioye
<pb facs="tcp:21187:60"/>God him ſelfe for euer and euer. Let vs therefore thinke vpon theſe thinges with al our heartes, affecte them with feruent deſyre, that wee may be the better able with ſpeede to come to them. If thou my ſoule per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture wilt aſke, by what helpe, or by whoſe merites maye this be done? Chriſt yelded himſelfe to death, to the ende to winne thee vnto the kingdome of God his father, Yelde thy ſelfe therfore vnto him, that ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thou maieſt bee of his kingdome. And let not ſynne haue dominion, nor reigne ouer thy mortal body, but let the ſoule be occupied in ſearching for euerlaſting life.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ A prayer that we ſhoulde repoſe our ſelues in God aboue all thinges.</head>
                  <p>O Ieſus, graunt, I beſeeche thee, that I maye reſt and repoſe my ſelf in thee before any creature, before al glory, honour, power, dignitie, and conſolation, ouer and aboue al hope
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:21187:60"/>and promiſe, yea, and aboue all the Angels, Archangels, and about all the hoſte of heauen, aboue al thinges viſible and inuiſible, and chief<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y, for that thou art my God, yea, thou a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e onely<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> God, excelling al other thinges. For thou a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t the higheſt, the moſte mightie, thou onely art the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ecteſt. O when ſhall it be fullye g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ted vnto me, that I ſhal forſake my ſelfe, and ſee howe ſweete and pleaſantly thou art, O Lord my God. O Ieſu, the brightnes of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal glory, the comfort of the wande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe ſoule, my mouthe is bent to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee without ſpeaking, and ſilence ſpeaketh vnto thee. How long wyl my Lord my God withdrawe himſelfe from commings vnto thee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> come vnto me thy ſeruant, comforte me O Lorde: thruſt foorth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinge hande, O God, and del<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap> me thy ſeruaunte from theſe troubles. Come, come, for without thee there can be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o reſtful day, nor quiet houre,
<pb facs="tcp:21187:61"/>Thou art my ioye, and without thee I am vnfurniſhed. Beholde a poore wretche howe. I am impryſoned, and my ſelfe loaden with Gyues, tyl thou deliuer mee, and refreſh mee with the light of thy preſence. Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe others ſearche thee at leyſure whenſoeuer it ſhal pleaſe them: Yet continuallye nothing ſhall pleaſe mee but thou my Lorde and GOD, my hope and eternal health. Bleſſed he thou, O Lords, which haſte done this goodneſſe vnto thy ſeruaunt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the multitude of thy mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye. What can thy ſeruant ſaye more vnto thee, O Lord, but humble him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in thy ſight, &amp; be alwayes mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of his iniquitye and vnwoorthy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes? For in al the wonderful thinges of heauen and earth, there is none like vnto thee. Thy workes are excel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lent, thy iudgementes are vpright, &amp; by thy prouidence al thinges are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned. O father of wiſedome, laude and praiſe be vnto thee. My mouth,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:21187:61"/>my ſoule, and al my powers ſhall prayſe thee without ceaſſing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ The ſoule feruently wiſheth to be in the houſe of the Lorde.</head>
                  <p>O Moſte bright and bewtifull houſe of the Lord, I am delyghted with thy comelineſſe, the habitation of the glory of my Lord, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> owner and buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of thee. Al my wandring perigri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation tendeth towardes thee, both night and daye, my heart coueteth to come vnto thee, my mynde is fullye bent towardes thee, my ſoule doeth feruently deſire to come into thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed company. I ſpeake this vnto him who made mee, and poſſeſſeth me in thee: for he created both thee and me. I do not aſke thy companye and the ſyght of thy wonderful pureneſſe, through mine own merites, but tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the bloud of him that hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed mee, whereof. I doe not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payre. I haue erred (I confeſſe) like a ſtraied ſheepe, and my dwelling is
<pb facs="tcp:21187:62"/>prolonged. I am caſte from the face of thee, O Lorde, in blyndnes of exile, wherin I am expulſed from the ioies of Paradiſe. I doo with ſorrowfull verſe and vnmeſurable lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, daily bewaile the miſeries of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y captiuitie, when I doo call thee to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce, O ſpirituall Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, and whileſt my feete ſtande in the excellent and beautiful Sion, not yet able openlye to ſee the innermoſt partes of thee: but yet I hope to be caried into thee vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſhoulders of my Redeemer, the verye builder of thee, that I maye reioyce with thee in that venerable glory, wherin they delight that are with thee in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God him ſelfe our redeemer, who hath diſſolued al enmitye that was betweene God and man with his owne fleſhe, and hath with his precious bloud pacifyed al thinges in heauen and earth. He is our peace, who hath made al things alone, who ioyning two walles in one in him
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:21187:62"/>ſelfe which before were diſagreeing, euerlaſtingly to continue in the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitie of his bleſſedneſſe. The ſame thinge hath hee promiſed vnto vs, ſaying. <hi>They ſhall be equall with the Angels of God in Heauen.</hi> Let me reioyce and be glad in thee, Let the ſweete memorye of thy bleſſed name be a releeuing of my ſorow and wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>¶ An earneſt prayer, that thou, being aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted by the grace of God, maieſt be alwaies bent to heauenly thinges.</head>
                  <p>I Would to God, that that daye might once ſhine, in the which I might ſee my redeemer, and al theſe temporal daies would ende. In thee (O heauenly kingdome) the ſain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes doo ſhine in perpetual and cleere charitie, which we can not ſee whilſt we wander here on earth. The hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenlye Citizens knowe how muche they them ſelues reioice: and the bani<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhed ſonnes of the <hi>Eua</hi> lament &amp; feele
<pb facs="tcp:21187:63"/>how bitter, werie, and tedious this worlde is. The dayes of this worlde are few, ſhorte, ful of euill and ſorow, where ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is defiled with many ſins, oppreſſed with grefes, troubled with cares, diſturbed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoughtes, wrapt in vanities, compaſſed with erroures moleſted with temptation, drowned in ſenſualitie, and crucified with po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertie. O when ſhal there be an ende of theſe manifolde and miſerable la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours? when ſhal I be deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the miſerable bondage of wickednes? When ſhall I onelye remember thee O Lorde? When ſhal I fullye and perfectly reioyce in thee? When ſhal I be out of al danger, deliuered from al griefe of bodye and ſoule, and come to true libertye? When ſhal I reſt in that quiete, ſecure and vndiſturbed peace? When ſhal I come thyther, where peace is both within &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out in althinges. O Lorde Ieſus, when ſhal I ſtande vp to ſee thee, when ſhal I behold the glorye of thy
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:21187:63"/>kingdome which thou haſt prepared for thine elect fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning? A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> poore wretche, I am left baniſhed in the lande of mine enemies, where there is dayly warres, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al miſfortune. Comfort me in my ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, mitigate my ſorowes, I do moſte feruentlye with all my heart require to come vnto thee: For wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoeuer pleaſure is offered vnto me in this worlde, I thinke it noyſome. I doo inwardly require thy companie, but I cannot obteine it. I doo wiſhe to be ioyned to heauenly thinges, but temporal pleaſures and mortal paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions keepeth me backe from them. In minde I woulde faine vanquiſhe al wickednes and vice, but yet I am conſtrained to be ſubiecte to the fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde fleſhe. And I vnhappye man am at controuerſy with my ſelfe, and am become odious vnto my ſelfe: for whileſt my ſoule aſpireth vpwarde, my fleſhe draweth downe warde. O what paſſions doo I inwardlye ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer:
<pb facs="tcp:21187:64"/>For when my ſoule beginneth to contemplate of heauenly things, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preſently heapes of carnall thoughts withdraweth me from prayers. O my God, doo not linger from me, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part not in anger from thy ſeruaunt. Thunder forth thy lightning bolts, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſperſe my worldly thoughts abrod, ſhoote thine arowes amongeſt them, &amp; driue away all the temptations of mine enemies. Turne my ſenſes vnto the make me forget al earthly things graunt, I beſeeche thee, that I may caſte off all ſinfull thoughtes and phantaſies. O eternall veritie, ſuccor me, to thend that no vanity, do tempt or remoue me from thee. O heauenly father helpe me, for al vanitie and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purenes melteth before thy face.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>An ardent deſire of the ſoule to the bleſſed and immortal life.</head>
                  <p>AS the Hart deſireth to come to the fountaines of freſhe waters, ſo doth my ſoule deſire to come to thee,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:21187:64"/>O Lorde. When ſhal I come and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere before thy face, O wel ſpryng of louing water? When ſhal I come to the water of thy ſweetenes, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this deſert, pathleſſe and barraine lande: that I may ſee thy vertue and glory, and coole my thirſt with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> water of thy mercye. O Lorde the wel of lyfe, ſatiſfye me, I thirſte for thee, O Lord God of life. When ſhal I come, O Lorde, and appeare before thy face? O moſte cleere and excellent daye without night, without ende, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I ſhal heare theſe wordes: <hi>Enter into the ioyes of the Lorde thy God.</hi> Enter in eternal glory into the houſe of thomnipotent God, where there is great and wonderful ioyes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out number. Enter into the glory, which is without ſorrowe, contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning eternal gladneſſe, where all goodneſſe and no euyl is, where the ſweete amiable way of life is, where is no controuerſy, neyther flickering intiſements, where there is a perfect
<pb facs="tcp:21187:65"/>and certaine aſſuraunce, an aſſured quietnes, a quiet pleaſantnes, a ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt happines, a happy eternity, an eternal bleſſednes, the bleſſed Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and vnity of Trinitie, deitie of v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, and a bleſſed ſyght of the deitie, which is the ioyes of thy Lord God. O ioye vpon ioy, and ioy aboue ioye, without whiche there is no ioye, when ſhal I enter into thee, that I maye ſee my God, who dwelleth in thee? I wyl go thither, and I wil ſee this moſt excellent ſyght. What is it that ſtayeth me? Wo be vnto me, for my daies are prolonged: wo be vnto mee, howe long ſhal it be ſayde vnto me, where is the Lord thy God? O my ſoule, attende a while, and expect that which I looke for. Shal not we attende the comming of our redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt who hath brought our bodies to their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient humility and obedience, confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guted and formed vnto the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of his owne body? Let vs abide
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21187:65"/>the returne of our Lorde from the mariage feaſte, to the ende hee maye leade vs vnto his mariage. Come, O Lorde, and ſtay not, come, O Lorde Ieſus Chriſte, come and viſite vs in peare, come and deliuer vs that he fettered out of priſon, that we maye reioyce before thee in perfectneſſe of hart. Come, our ſauiour, the wiſhed hope of al people, ſhewe thy face, and we ſhalbe ſaued. Come my light, my rede<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>er, deliuer my foule out of this priſon, that it may confeſſe and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye thy holy name. Howe longe ſhall I bee toſte in the ſurging waues of this my mortal life, crying vnto thee and thou wilt not heare me. Heare me, O Lorde, calling vnto thee from this large, troubleſome and daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous Sea, and bring mee vnto thy ſafe porte of eternal felicities. O hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pye are they that haue through thy goodnes ariued from al the dangers of this Sea, in that moſt ſafe porte and harborough of reſt. O moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
<pb facs="tcp:21187:66"/>are they which haue eſcaped this ſurging Seas, and are ſafely landed vpon the ſhores, eſcaped this pryſon, and come to thy Palace, returned from exile, and entred into thy king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. The bleſſed doo moſte quickly enioye that they wiſhed for. Happy are they that haue obteined the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>war<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e of eternal glorye, and that which here they haue won in tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation they do nowe ioyfully broo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e in happy myrth and perpetual glory. Moſt bleſſed &amp; thriſe fouretimes bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are they whiche haue obteyned throughe his aboundante glorye to come to his gracious kingdome. O eternal kingdome, and kingdome of all worldes, where there is conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual lyght, and where the peace of God is, which doeth farre exceede at vnderſtanding, wherin the ſoules of the elect do reſt, replete with eternal gladneſſe. Oglorious is thy kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, wherein al the ſaints do reigne appareled with white garmentes,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:21187:66"/>hauing crownes vpon theyr heades. O kingdome of eternal bliſſe. O hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pye kingdome, where thou, O Lord, the Diadem of glorye ſhalt be ſeene face to face, reioycing them in thy peace, whiche paſſeth al capacitye. Happy are they therefore that haue eſcaped from the ſhipwracke of this life, and haue obteyned to come into ſo great ioy and gladnes. Vnhappye (alas) are wee poore wretches, that do row our ſhip through the deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring waues of this large raging ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not knowing when we ſhal come to that hauen of health. Vnhappy (I ſay) are they who leade theyr lyues in exile and daunger, whoſe ende is doubtful. For we knowe not what ſhal become of vs, for al thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s which are to come, are vnknowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. We as yet ſayling in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues of the Sea, doo hope and looke to come to the happy porte and haue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ourcountrey. O ſafe countrey, we ſee thee a farre off, we ſalute thee fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <pb facs="tcp:21187:67"/>the Seas, we doo ſigh and wiſhe to come to thee out of this vale, and we doo endenour our ſelues, yea, with teares, to ſee, if by anye meanes wee may come vnto thee. O Chriſte, the God of Gods, and hope of humaine kind, our refuge and ſtrength, whoſe lyght our eyes doo beholde through the thicke clouds aboue, through the boyſterous ſtormes of this trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Seas (as the bright beames of the careful ſhipmans ſtarre) ende ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring out ſelues thereby to direct our courſe vnto thy hauen and ſafe har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borough, O Lord, gouerne our ſhip in thy right hande with the nailes of thy croſſe, that we do not periſhe in the roaring waues, nor tempeſt drowne vs, nor be ſunke downe in the deepe: but faſten the anker of thy croſſe vnto our ſhip, and draw vs out of this ſea vnto thy ſelfe, our onely comfort and conſolation. He holde vs whom thou haſt redeemed with thy precious bloud, and nowe baniſhed
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:21187:67"/>from thee, we do cal vpon thee, heare vs O God our Sauiour, the onelye hope of al thoſe that dwel in al the corners of the earth, we are toſte in the troubleſome ſeas, and thou on the ſhore doſt ſee our daunger. Saue vs for thy names ſake, and graunt vnto vs O Lord, I beſeech thee, that we which ſaile betweene Silla and Charibdin, may ſo ſterne and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne our Sip vnto thee, that eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caping both the daungers, we may be preſerued both Sippe and wares, ſafely ariuing vnto thy Porte and hauen of reſt.</p>
                  <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:21187:68"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A breefe Table of the thinges conteyned in this Booke, wiſhing the Reader to peruſe it throughly.</head>
            <list>
               <item>OF the fall of mán, and the puniſhment by death for the ſame, and of the uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine hower of death. Fol. <hi>1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Death. Iudgement, Hell, &amp; Heauen. Fol. <hi>2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the hower of Death worthy of often repetition. Fol. <hi>3</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A ready inſtruction and godly exerciſe for an happy death, ſpoken as it were in the per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon of Chriſt to the ſoule. Fol. <hi>6</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Holſome admonitions to dye. Fol. <hi>13</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An exerciſe to be vſed in the morning, or al other times when you thinke good. Fol. <hi>15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Counſailes at the hower of death. Fol. <hi>18</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An exerciſe wherin the weake man may reſtane him ſelfe vnto God Fol. <hi>19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Chriſtian proteſtation or laſt teſtament not vnprofitable to be ſayd or to be thought vppon. Fol. <hi>22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How feareful and bitter corporal death is of it ſelfe, and the naturall cauſes thereof. Fol. <hi>24</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:21187:68"/>
               <item>The manner to dye well. Fol. <hi>17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The certentye of Death, and the vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne hower thereof. Fol. <hi>27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Why the iuſt men do wiſh for death. Fol. <hi>28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The death of the iuſt man Fol. <hi>30</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The death of the euill. Fol. <hi>31</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The daungers of death. Fol. <hi>31</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How we ſhould comforte thoſe that be in daunger of death. Fol. <hi>32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Three exhortations to the ſicke. Fol. <hi>33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Queſtions to be aſked him that lyeth ſick, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſter, or ſome other godly perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Fol. <hi>33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Praiers to be ſaid at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hower of death. Fol. <hi>34</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Howe to foreſee that thinges go rightlye with any when be dyeth. Fol. <hi>35</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A briefe Dialogue touthing the daye of iudgement. Fol. <hi>37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A general iudgement of the dead<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth an vniuerſall reſurrection. Fol. <hi>38</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the excellencie of the iudgement days aboue al other dayes. Fol. <hi>41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the paines of hell. Fol. <hi>43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of hel. Fol. <hi>44</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Meditations of the heauenly kingdome. Fol. <hi>46</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The defyre the ſoule hath to the heauenly Hieruſalem. Fol. <hi>47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How plentifull of all goodneſſe, and howe ſpare of al euil the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly Ieruſalem is. Fol. <hi>49</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:21187:69"/>
               <item>A ſuppoſed deſcription of the heauénlye Hieruſalem. Fol. <hi>50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the perfect and abſolute ioy of eternal lyfe. Fol. <hi>51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer whereby thou maiſt be fryred vp vnto the deſyre of heauenly thinges. Fol. <hi>53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Man wiſheth for the trybulations of this world, to the end that he may the more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſyre the kingdome of heauen. Fol. <hi>55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A prayer that we ſhould depoſe our ſelues in God aboue al thinges. Fol. <hi>56</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The ſoule feruently wiſheth to be in the houſe of the Lord. Fol. <hi>58</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An earneſt prayer, that being aſſiſted by the grace of God, we may be alwayes bent to heauenly thinges. Fol. <hi>59</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An ardent deſire of the ſoule to the bleſſed and immortall lyfe. Fol. <hi>60</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:21187:69"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
